<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Account"
  xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright>Copyright (C) 2008 Collabora Ltd.</tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright>Copyright (C) 2008 Nokia Corporation</tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.
</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Account">
    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>An Account object encapsulates the necessary details to make a
        Telepathy connection.</p>

      <p>Accounts are uniquely identified by object path. The object path
        of an Account MUST take the form
        <code>/org/freedesktop/Telepathy/Account/<em>cm</em>/<em>proto</em>/<em>acct</em></code>, where:</p>

      <ul>
        <li><em>cm</em> is the same <tp:type>Connection_Manager_Name</tp:type>
          that appears in the connection manager's well-known bus name and
          object path</li>
        <li><em>proto</em> is the <tp:type>Protocol</tp:type> name as seen in
          ConnectionManager.ListProtocols, but with "-" replaced with "_"
          (i.e. the same as in the object-path of a Connection)</li>
        <li><em>acct</em> is an arbitrary string of ASCII letters, digits
          and underscores, starting with a letter or underscore, which
          uniquely identifies this account</li>
        <li>Clients SHOULD parse the object path to discover the
          connection manager and protocol</li>
        <li>Clients MUST NOT attempt to parse <em>acct</em></li>
        <li>Clients MUST NOT assume that <em>acct</em> matches
          the connection-specific part of a Connection's object-path and
          bus name</li>
        <li>The account manager SHOULD choose <em>acct</em> such that if
          an account is deleted, its object path will be re-used if and only
          if the new account is in some sense "the same"
          (incorporating the 'account' parameter in some way is
          recommended)</li>
      </ul>

      <tp:rationale>
        <p>This API avoids specifying the "profiles" used in Mission Control
          4.x or the "presets" that have been proposed to replace them. An
          optional interface will be provided for AM implementations
          that want to provide presets.</p>

        <p>There is deliberately no functionality here for opening channels;
          we intend to provide that in the channel dispatcher.</p>

        <p>Other missing features which would be better in their own
          interfaces:</p>

        <ul>
          <li>dynamic parameter-providing (aka provisioning)</li>
          <li>saved server capabilities</li>
          <li>account conditions</li>
          <li>account grouping</li>
        </ul>
      </tp:rationale>

    </tp:docstring>
    <tp:added version="0.17.2"/>
    <tp:changed version="0.17.6">moved the Avatar property to a separate
      interface</tp:changed>

    <!-- Missing functionality compared with NMC 4.x account + profile,
    apart from as listed above:

    * vCard field, + default profile for each vCard field
      (vCard field is per protocol and should be chosen by the
      Telepathy <-> address-book bridge?; default profile is now
      meaningless)

    * "normalized name" (normalized handle?)

    * branding icon (what's this and how does it differ from the icon?)

    * configuration UI (not our problem - perhaps the UI could special-case
      by cm,protocol,preset tuples?)

    * default account domain (somewhat meaningless in general; specialized
      account config UI can hard-code this)

    * SPLIT_ACCOUNT (pseudo-capability - this is a property of the protocol,
      not the profile, and in any case only the account config UI cares)

    Missing functionality compared with Decibel accounts:

    * we don't really know, they take arbitrary key/value pairs...
      but display name, protocol, presence/message, current, autoreconnect
      are the ones given special status by the source, and we have all of them
    -->

    <property name="Interfaces" type="as" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        A list of the extra interfaces provided by this account.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <method name="Remove">
      <tp:docstring>Delete the account.</tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.PermissionDenied"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <signal name="Removed">
      <tp:docstring>
        This account has been removed.

        <tp:rationale>
          This is redundant with AccountRemoved, but it's still worth having,
          to avoid having to bind to AccountManager.AccountRemoved to tell
          you whether your Account is valid - ideally, an account-editing UI
          should only care about a single Account.
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </signal>

    <signal name="AccountPropertyChanged">
      <tp:docstring>
        The values of one or more properties on this interface (that do not
        specify that this signal does not apply to them) may have changed.
        This does not cover properties of other interfaces, which must
        provide their own change notification if appropriate.
      </tp:docstring>

      <arg name="Properties" type="a{sv}">
        <tp:docstring>
          A map from property names in this namespace (e.g. Nickname) to
          values. Properties whose values have not changed SHOULD be
          omitted, but this need not be done.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
    </signal>

    <property name="DisplayName" type="s" access="readwrite">
      <tp:docstring>
        The user-visible name of this account. This SHOULD be chosen by the
        user at account creation time. The account creation user interface
        is responsible for setting a reasonable default value in the user's
        locale; something like "Jabber (bob@example.com)" would be sensible.

        <tp:rationale>
          This approximately corresponds to "display name" in NMC 4.x and
          Decibel.
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="Icon" type="s" access="readwrite">
      <tp:docstring>
        The name of an icon in the system's icon theme, such as "im-msn",
        or the empty string to not specify an icon. If the icon is set to
        an empty string, the account manager or any client MAY derive a
        default icon, for instance from the protocol.

        <tp:rationale>
          This approximately corresponds to mc_profile_get_icon_name
          (or possibly mc_profile_get_branding_icon_name) in NMC 4.x.
          It's accessed via the account rather than the profile because
          we no longer have profiles as a core concept.
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="Valid" type="b" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        If true, this account is considered by the account manager to be
        complete and usable. If false, user action is required to make it
        usable, and it will never attempt to connect (for instance, this
        might be caused by the absence of a required parameter).

        <tp:rationale>
          For connection managers with a plugin architecture, like
          telepathy-haze, we have little or no control over the parameters
          offered; for platforms with package management, we have little or
          no control over the CMs offered. NMC 4.x would just pretend the
          account didn't exist in these circumstances, but silent data loss
          is bad, and UIs with CM-specific knowledge (or a user filling in
          newly-required parameters) might be able to rescue a broken account.
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="Enabled" type="b" access="readwrite">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>This property gives the users the possibility to prevent an account
          from being used. This flag does not change the validity of the
          account.</p>

        <p>A disabled account can never be put online.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>Use cases:</p>

          <ul>
            <li>user has two or more accounts capable of calling contact X, but
              he doesn't want the UI to prompt him everytime about which one he
              wants to use for the call. He can then disable all the equivalent
              accounts but one.</li>

            <li>There is some temporary server error and the user doesn't want
              to be be bother by error messages, or change the account
              configuration: temporarily disabling the account is quicker.</li>
          </ul>

          <p>The AccountManager SHOULD allow this property to be set on invalid
            accounts, but MUST NOT attempt to put invalid accounts online
            even if they become Enabled.</p>

          <tp:rationale>
            <p>There doesn't seem to be any good reason not to allow this.</p>
          </tp:rationale>
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="Nickname" type="as" access="readwrite">
      <tp:docstring>
        The nickname to set on this account for display to other contacts,
        as set by the user. When the account becomes connected, the
        account manager SHOULD set this as the user's alias using SetAliases
        if appropriate.

        <tp:rationale>
          In a later specification revision, we plan to separate the concepts
          of a contact's nickname as set by themselves, and the local
          name for them in our contact list (a "handle" or "pet name" as
          described in XEP-0165 and its references). The terminology change
          from alias to nickname here is a step in that direction.
          This corresponds to NMC 4.x mc_account_get_alias.
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="Parameters" type="a{sv}" access="read">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>A map from connection manager parameter names (as in the
          ConnectionManager interface) to their values. This property includes
          only those parameters that are stored for this account, and SHOULD
          only include those parameters that the user has explicitly set.
        </p>
        <p>This property cannot be altered using Set() - use
          UpdateParameters instead.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          This avoids NMC being tied to gconf as a matter of API.
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <method name="UpdateParameters">
      <tp:docstring>
        Change the value of the Parameters property. Any changes will not
        take effect until the next time the account is disconnected and
        reconnected.

        <tp:rationale>
          Migration tools that twiddle the settings of all accounts shouldn't
          cause an automatic disconnect and reconnect, probably. I could be
          persuaded otherwise, though. Or we could add a Reconnect() method.
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>

      <arg name="Set" type="a{sv}" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          A mapping from parameter names to their values. These parameters
          should be stored for future use.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="Unset" type="as" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          A list of the names of parameters to be removed from the set of
          stored values, allowing the default values to be used.
          If the given parameters were not, in fact, stored, or even if they
          do not exist at all, the account manager MUST accept this without
          error.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.PermissionDenied"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidArgument"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <tp:struct name="Account_Presence">
      <tp:docstring>
        A simplified form of the presence statuses seen in the Presence
        interface.
      </tp:docstring>

      <tp:member name="Type" type="u" tp:type="Connection_Presence_Type">
        <tp:docstring>
          The presence type, e.g. Connection_Presence_Type_Away.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>

      <tp:member name="Status" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          The connection-manager-specific string identifier of the presence
          status, e.g. "brb".
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>

      <tp:member name="Message" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          The user-defined status message, e.g. "Back soon!". This will be
          used as the value for the 'message' keyword in the Presence
          interface's dictionary, if possible.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
    </tp:struct>

    <property name="AutomaticPresence" type="(uss)" access="readwrite"
      tp:type="Account_Presence">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The presence status that this account should have if it is brought
          online.</p>

        <p>Setting this property MUST NOT actually change the account's
          status until the next time it is (re)connected for some reason.</p>

        <p>The <tp:type>Connection_Presence_Type</tp:type> in the structure
          SHOULD NOT be Offline or Unset.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          In ITOS2007 and ITOS2008 this is a global preference, not visible
          on D-Bus (the "default presence"). "Automatic presence" better
          describes when it is used.
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="ConnectAutomatically" type="b" access="readwrite">
      <tp:docstring>
        If true, the account manager SHOULD attempt to put this account
        online with the AutomaticPresence whenever possible (in the base
        Account interface this is deliberately left vague). If false,
        it MUST NOT put the account online automatically in response to,
        for instance, connectivity changes, but SHOULD still put the account
        online with the AutomaticPresence if requested by the user (for
        instance, if the user tries to start a conversation using this
        account).

        <tp:rationale>
          This approximately corresponds to NMC 4.x "enabled" and Decibel
          "autoreconnect".
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="Connection" type="s" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        Either the well-known bus name of the connection to this account,
        or the empty string if there is no connection.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="ConnectionStatus" type="u" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        If the Connection property is non-empty, the status of that connection.
        If the Connection property is the empty string, this property may
        either be Disconnected (indicating that the account manager is not
        attempting to bring it online), or Connecting (indicating that the
        account manager is attempting to connect).
        The account manager is expected to set this by observing signals
        from the Connection.

        <tp:rationale>
          If the AM is doing some sort of backoff/delay on reconnection
          attempts, the account's status is conceptually "Connecting" even
          though there is no Connection. This vaguely corresponds to
          GetCurrentStatus in NMC 4.x.
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="ConnectionStatusReason" type="u" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        The reason for the last change to ConnectionStatus.
        The account manager is expected to set this by observing signals
        from the Connection.

        <tp:rationale>
          If you weren't watching the Connection at the time it failed,
          you can't tell why - unless the AM can tell you. This is part
          of GetCurrentStatus in NMC 4.x.
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="CurrentPresence" type="(uss)" access="read"
      tp:type="Account_Presence">
      <tp:docstring>
        The actual presence. If the connection is not online, this should be
        (Connection_Presence_Type_Offline, "", "").
        If the connection is online but does not support the Presence
        interface, this should be (Connection_Presence_Type_Unset, "", "").
        The account manager is expected to set this by observing signals
        from the Connection.

        <tp:rationale>
          This corresponds to GetPresenceActual in NMC 4.x.
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="RequestedPresence" type="(uss)" access="readwrite"
      tp:type="Account_Presence">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The requested presence for this account. When this is changed, the
          account manager should attempt to manipulate the connection manager
          to make CurrentPresence match RequestedPresence as closely as
          possible. It should not be saved to any sort of persistent
          storage.</p>

        <p>When the account manager automatically connects an account,
          it must signal this by setting the RequestedPresence to the same
          thing as the AutomaticPresence.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          This corresponds to e.g. GetPresence and GetPresenceMessage
          in NMC 4.x.
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="NormalizedName" type="s" access="read">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The normalized user ID of the local user on this account (i.e. the
          string returned when the InspectHandle method is called on the
          result of GetSelfHandle() for an active connection).</p>
        
        <p>It is unspecified whether this user ID is globally unique.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>As currently implemented, IRC user IDs are only unique within
            the same IRCnet. On some saner protocols, the user ID includes a
            DNS name which provides global uniqueness.</p>
        </tp:rationale>

        <p>If this value is not known yet (which will always be the case for
          accounts that have never been online), it will be an empty
          string.</p>

        <p>It is possible that this value will change if the connection
          manager's normalization algorithm changes, although this SHOULD
          be avoided.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>It's not always completely clear what normalization algorithm
            should be used; for instance, in Gabble, we currently use JIDs,
            but it would also have been reasonable to use xmpp URIs.</p>
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
