<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Account_Interface_Hidden"
  xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">

  <tp:copyright>Copyright © 2010 Collabora Ltd.</tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
      modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
      License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
      version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

    <p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
      but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
      MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
      Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

    <p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
      License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
      Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA
      02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>

  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Account.Interface.Hidden.DRAFT1"
    tp:causes-havoc="outrageous">
    <tp:added version="0.21.10">(draft 1)</tp:added>

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>An interface for flagging certain accounts as hidden, so that they do
        not appear in the account manager's standard lists of accounts.
        Accounts whose <tp:member-ref>Hidden</tp:member-ref> property is
        <code>True</code> are intended for non-interactive use (by
        non-user-visible services), and appear on the <tp:dbus-ref
          namespace='ofdT'>AccountManager.Interface.Hidden.DRAFT1</tp:dbus-ref>
        interface; in all other respects, they behave like any other
        account.</p>

      <tp:rationale>
        <p>XMPP, in particular, is increasingly used for purposes other than
          instant messaging and VoIP. For instance, extensions exist for
          inter-device bookmark synchronization.</p>

        <p>While obviously these services could re-use connections intended for
          instant messaging, in some cases you might want to use a different
          account. (Perhaps your bookmark sync provider is not your IM
          provider.) This API allows such auxiliary accounts to exist in
          Telepathy, while not being displayed in standard user interfaces for
          IM, VoIP, and friends.</p>
      </tp:rationale>
    </tp:docstring>

    <property name="Hidden" tp:name-for-bindings="Hidden"
              type="b" access="read" tp:immutable='aye'>
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>If <code>True</code>, this account is intended for non-interactive
          use, and thus should not be presented to the user. It will not appear
          in properties and signals on the main <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace='ofdT'>AccountManager</tp:dbus-ref> interface; instead, it
          will show up on <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace='ofdT'>AccountManager.Interface.Hidden.DRAFT1</tp:dbus-ref>.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
