<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Call_Content_Media_Description_Interface_RTP_Header_Extensions" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright> Copyright © 2005-2010 Nokia Corporation </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright © 2005-2010 Collabora Ltd </tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.
  </tp:license>

  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Call1.Content.MediaDescription.Interface.RTPHeaderExtensions">
    <tp:added version="0.25.2">(as stable API)</tp:added>
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Call1.Content.MediaDescription"/>

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>This media description interface provides a method of signalling
        support for RTP Header Extensions, documented by
        <em>A General Mechanism for RTP Header Extensions (RFC 5285)</em>.</p>

      <p>For more details on the General Mechanism for RTP Header Extensions
         and how to use them, one should refer to
        <a href="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc5285.html">RFC 5285</a>.</p>

    </tp:docstring>

    <tp:struct name="RTP_Header_Extension"
      array-name="RTP_Header_Extensions_List">
      <tp:docstring>
        A struct defining a RTP Header extension.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:member type="u" name="ID">
        <tp:docstring>
          Identifier to be negotiated.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Media_Stream_Direction"  name="Direction">
        <tp:docstring>
          Direction in which the Header Extension is negotiated.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="s" name="URI">
        <tp:docstring>
          URI defining the extension.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="s" name="Parameters">
        <tp:docstring>
          Feedback parameters as a string. Format is defined in the relevant RFC.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
    </tp:struct>

    <property name="HeaderExtensions" type="a(uuss)"
      tp:type="RTP_Header_Extension[]"
      access="read" tp:name-for-bindings="Header_Extensions">
      <tp:docstring>
        A list of remote header extensions which are supported.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>
  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
