<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Call_Content_Media_Description_Interface_RTCP_Feedback" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright> Copyright © 2005-2010 Nokia Corporation </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright © 2005-2010 Collabora Ltd </tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.
  </tp:license>

  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Call1.Content.MediaDescription.Interface.RTCPFeedback">
    <tp:added version="0.25.2">(as stable API)</tp:added>
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Call1.Content.MediaDescription"/>

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>This codec offer interface provides a method of signalling
        support for RTCP feedback, documented by <em>Extended RTP
        Profile for Real-time Transport Control Protocol (RTCP)-Based
        Feedback (RTP/AVPF)</em> (RFC 4585).</p>

      <p>The codec identifiers used in the description of the Feedback Messages
      sent in the <tp:dbus-ref
        namespace="ofdT.Call1.Content.MediaDescription">Accept</tp:dbus-ref>'s
      should match those used for the RemoteCodecs in the same Accept call.
      </p>

      <p>For more details on what RTCP Feedback can do and how to use
        it, one should refer to
        <a href="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc4585.html">RFC 4585</a>.</p>

    </tp:docstring>

    <property name="FeedbackMessages" type="a{u(ua(sss))}"
      tp:type="RTCP_Feedback_Message_Map"
      access="read" tp:name-for-bindings="Feedback_Messages">
      <tp:docstring>
        A map of remote feedback codec properties that are supported.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="DoesAVPF" type="b"
      access="read" tp:name-for-bindings="Does_AVPF">
      <tp:docstring>
        True if the remote contact supports Audio-Visual Profile
        Feedback (AVPF), otherwise False.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>
  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
