<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Channel_Interface_Tube" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright>Copyright © 2008-2009 Collabora Limited</tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright>Copyright © 2008-2009 Nokia Corporation</tp:copyright>
  <tp:license>
    This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface.Tube.DRAFT"
      tp:causes-havoc="experimental">
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel"/>
    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>A <i>tube</i> is a mechanism for arbitrary data transfer between
      two or more IM users, used to allow applications on the users'
      systems to communicate without having to establish network
      connections themselves. Currently, two types of tube exist:
      <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy"
      >Channel.Type.DBusTube.DRAFT</tp:dbus-ref> and
      <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy"
      >Channel.Type.StreamTube.DRAFT</tp:dbus-ref>. This interface contains
      the properties, signals and methods common to both types of tube;
      you can only create channels of a specific tube type, not of this
      type. A tube channel contains exactly one tube; if you need several
      tubes, you have to create several tube channels.</p>

      <p>Tube channels can be requested for handles of type
      HANDLE_TYPE_CONTACT (for 1-1 communication) or of type
      HANDLE_TYPE_ROOM (to communicate with others in the room
      simultaneously).</p>

      <p>As an exception to the usual handling of capabilities, connection managers
        for protocols with capability discovery, such as XMPP, SHOULD advertise the
        capability representing each Tube type that they support
       (<tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Channel.Type.DBusTube.DRAFT</tp:dbus-ref> and/or
        <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Channel.Type.StreamTube.DRAFT</tp:dbus-ref>)
        even if no client has indicated via
        <tp:dbus-ref
          namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.ContactCapabilities.DRAFT">SetSelfCapabilities</tp:dbus-ref>
        that such a tube is supported.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>To lower the barrier entry of new tube application, CM SHOULD accept to offer tubes of any
            <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Type.StreamTube.DRAFT">Service</tp:dbus-ref> or
            <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Type.DBusTube.DRAFT">ServiceName</tp:dbus-ref>
            if the contact announced to support tubes.</p>
        </tp:rationale>
    </tp:docstring>

    <property name="Parameters" type="a{sv}" tp:type="String_Variant_Map"
              access="read" tp:name-for-bindings="Parameters">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Each tube has a dictionary of arbitrary parameters. Parameters are
          commonly used to bootstrap legacy protocols where you can't
          negotiate parameters in-band. The allowable keys,
          types and values are defined by the service. Connection managers
          must support the value being a string (D-Bus type 's'), array of bytes
          (D-Bus type 'ay'), unsigned integer (D-Bus type 'u'), integer (D-Bus
          type 'i') and boolean (D-Bus type 'b').</p>
        <p>When the tube is offered, the parameters are transmitted with the
          offer and appear as a property of the incoming tube for other
          participants.</p>
        <p>Example of valid parameters for 'smb' Server Message Block over
          TCP/IP (from <a href="http://www.dns-sd.org/ServiceTypes.html">DNS
          SRV (RFC 2782) Service Types
          http://www.dns-sd.org/ServiceTypes.html</a>):
          <code>{'u': 'username', 'p': 'password', 'path': 'path'}</code></p>
        <p>When requesting a channel with
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Connection.Interface.Requests.CreateChannel</tp:dbus-ref>,
          this property MUST NOT be included in the request. This property is undefined until the tube is offered
          (using <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Type.StreamTube.DRAFT">OfferStreamTube</tp:dbus-ref>
          or <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Type.DBusTube.DRAFT">OfferDBusTube</tp:dbus-ref>).
          Once it has been offered, this property MUST NOT change.</p>
        <p>When receiving an incoming tube, this property is immutable and so advertised in the
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Connection.Interface.Requests.NewChannels</tp:dbus-ref>
          signal.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="State" type="u" tp:type="Tube_Channel_State" access="read"
              tp:name-for-bindings="State">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>State of the tube in this channel.</p>
        <p>When requesting a channel with
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Connection.Interface.Requests.CreateChannel</tp:dbus-ref>,
          this property MUST NOT be included in the request.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <tp:enum name="Tube_Channel_State" type="u">
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Local_Pending" value="0">
        <tp:docstring>
          The initiator offered the tube. The tube is waiting to be
          accepted/closed locally. If the client accepts the tube, the tube's
          state will be Open.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Remote_Pending" value="1">
        <tp:docstring>
          The tube is waiting to be accepted/closed remotely. If the
          recipient accepts the tube, the tube's state will be Open.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Open" value="2">
        <tp:docstring>
          The initiator offered the tube and the recipient accepted it. The
          tube is open for traffic. The tube's state stays in this state until
          it is closed.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Not_Offered" value="3">
        <tp:docstring>
          The tube channel has been requested but the tube is not yet offered.
          The client should offer the tube to the recipient and the tube's
          state will be Remote_Pending. The method to offer the tube depend on
          the tube type.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
    </tp:enum>

    <signal name="TubeChannelStateChanged"
            tp:name-for-bindings="Tube_Channel_State_Changed">
      <tp:docstring>
        Emitted when the state of the tube channel changes.
      </tp:docstring>
      <arg name="state" type="u" tp:type="Tube_Channel_State">
        <tp:docstring>
          The new state of the tube; see the Tube_Channel_State enumeration.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
    </signal>

  </interface>

</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
