<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Channel_Interface_Conference"
  xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright>Copyright © 2009 Collabora Limited</tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright>Copyright © 2009 Nokia Corporation</tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
      modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
      License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
      version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

    <p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
      but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
      MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
      Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

    <p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
      License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
      Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA
      02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface
    name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface.Conference.DRAFT"
    tp:causes-havoc="experimental">
    <tp:added version="0.19.0">(draft 1)</tp:added>
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel"/>
    <tp:requires
      interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface.Group"/>

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>An interface for multi-user conference channels that can "continue
        from" one or more individual channels.</p>

      <tp:rationale>
        <p>This interface addresses freedesktop.org <a
            href="http://bugs.freedesktop.org/show_bug.cgi?id=24906">bug
            #24906</a> (GSM-compatible conference calls) and <a
            href="http://bugs.freedesktop.org/show_bug.cgi?id=24939">bug
            #24939</a> (upgrading calls and chats to multi-user).
          See those bugs for rationale and use cases.</p>

        <p>Examples of usage:</p>

        <p>Active and held GSM calls C1, C2 can be merged into a single
          channel Cn with the Conference interface, by calling
          <code>CreateChannel({...ChannelType: ...Call,
            ...<tp:member-ref>InitialChannels</tp:member-ref>: [C1, C2]})</code>
          which returns Cn.</p>

        <p>An XMPP 1-1 conversation C1 can be continued in a newly created
          multi-user chatroom Cn by calling
          <code>CreateChannel({...ChannelType: ...Text,
            ...<tp:member-ref>InitialChannels</tp:member-ref>: [C1]})</code>
          which returns Cn.</p>

        <p>An XMPP 1-1 conversation C1 can be continued in a specified
          multi-user chatroom by calling
          <code>CreateChannel({...ChannelType: ...Text, ...HandleType: ROOM,
            ...TargetID: 'telepathy@conf.example.com',
            ...<tp:member-ref>InitialChannels</tp:member-ref>: [C1]})</code>
          which returns a Conference channel.</p>

        <p>Either of the XMPP cases could work for Call channels, to
          upgrade from 1-1 Jingle to multi-user Muji. Any of the XMPP cases
          could in principle work for link-local XMPP (XEP-0174).</p>

        <p>The underlying switchboard representing an MSN 1-1 conversation C1
          with a contact X can be moved to a representation as a nameless
          chatroom, Cn, to which more contacts can be invited, by calling
          <code>CreateChannel({...ChannelType: ...Text,
            ...<tp:member-ref>InitialChannels</tp:member-ref>: [C1]})</code>
          which returns Cn. C1 SHOULD remain open, with no underlying
          switchboard attached. If X establishes a new switchboard with the
          local user, C1 SHOULD pick up that switchboard rather than letting
          it create a new channel.
          <strong>[FIXME: should it?]</strong>
          Similarly, if the local user sends a message in C1, then
          a new switchboard to X should be created and associated with C1.</p>

        <p>XMPP and MSN do not natively have a concept of merging two or more
          channels C1, C2... into one channel, Cn. However, the GSM-style
          merging API can be supported on XMPP and MSN, as an API short-cut
          for upgrading C1 into a conference Cn (which invites the
          TargetHandle of C1 into Cn), then immediately inviting the
          TargetHandle of C2, the TargetHandle of C3, etc. into Cn as well.</p>

        <p>With a suitable change of terminology, Skype has behaviour similar
          to MSN.</p>
      </tp:rationale>

      <p>The <tp:dbus-ref
          namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface"
          >Group</tp:dbus-ref> MAY have channel-specific handles for participants;
        clients SHOULD support both Conferences that have channel-specific handles,
        and those that do not.</p>

      <tp:rationale>
        <p>In the GSM case, the Conference's Group interface MAY have
          channel-specific handles, to reflect the fact that the identities of
          the participants might not be known - it can be possible to know that
          there is another participant in the Conference, but not know who
          they are.
          <strong>[FIXME: fact check from GSM gurus needed]</strong>
        </p>

        <p>In the XMPP case, the Conference's Group interface SHOULD have
          channel-specific handles, to reflect the fact that the participants
          have MUC-specific identities, and the user might also be able to see
          their global identities, or not.</p>

        <p>In most other cases, including MSN and link-local XMPP, the
          Conference's Group interface SHOULD NOT have channel-specific
          handles, since users' identities are always visible.</p>
      </tp:rationale>

      <p>Connection managers implementing channels with this interface
        MUST NOT allow the object paths of channels that could be merged
        into a Conference to be re-used, unless the channel re-using the
        object path is equivalent to the channel that previously used it.</p>

      <tp:rationale>
        <p>If you upgrade some channels into a conference, and then close
          the original channels, <tp:member-ref>InitialChannels</tp:member-ref>
          (which is immutable) will contain paths to channels which no longer
          exist. This implies that you should not re-use channel object paths,
          unless future incarnations of the path are equivalent.</p>

        <p>For instance, on protocols where you can only have
          zero or one 1-1 text channels with Emily at one time, it would
          be OK to re-use the same object path for every 1-1 text channel
          with Emily; but on protocols where this is not true, it would
          be misleading.</p>
      </tp:rationale>

    </tp:docstring>

    <property name="Channels" tp:name-for-bindings="Channels"
      access="read" type="ao">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The individual <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Channel</tp:dbus-ref>s that
          are continued by this conference, which have the same <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel"
              >ChannelType</tp:dbus-ref> as this one, but with <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel"
              >TargetHandleType</tp:dbus-ref> = CONTACT.</p>

        <p>This property MUST NOT be requestable.
          <strong>[FIXME: or would it be better for this one, and not IC, to be
            requestable?]</strong>
        </p>

        <p>Change notification is via the
          <tp:member-ref>ChannelMerged</tp:member-ref> and
          <tp:member-ref>ChannelRemoved</tp:member-ref> signals.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <signal name="ChannelMerged" tp:name-for-bindings="Channel_Merged">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Emitted when a new channel is added to the value of
          <tp:member-ref>Channels</tp:member-ref>.</p>
      </tp:docstring>

      <arg name="Channel" type="o">
        <tp:docstring>The channel that was added to
          <tp:member-ref>Channels</tp:member-ref>.</tp:docstring>
      </arg>
    </signal>

    <signal name="ChannelRemoved" tp:name-for-bindings="Channel_Removed">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Emitted when a channel is removed from the value of
          <tp:member-ref>Channels</tp:member-ref>, either because it closed
          or because it was split using the <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface"
            >Splittable.DRAFT.Split</tp:dbus-ref> method.</p>

        <p><strong>[FIXME: relative ordering of this vs. Closed? Do we
            care?]</strong></p>
      </tp:docstring>

      <arg name="Channel" type="o">
        <tp:docstring>The channel that was removed from
          <tp:member-ref>Channels</tp:member-ref>.</tp:docstring>
      </arg>
    </signal>

    <property name="InitialChannels" tp:name-for-bindings="Initial_Channels"
      access="read" type="ao">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The initial value of <tp:member-ref>Channels</tp:member-ref>.</p>

        <p>This property SHOULD be requestable. Omitting it from a request is
          equivalent to providing it with an empty list as value. Requests
          where its value has at least two elements SHOULD be expected to
          succeed on any implementation of this interface.</p>

        <p>Whether a request with 0 or 1 elements in the list will succeed is
          indicated by <tp:member-ref>SupportsNonMerges</tp:member-ref>.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>In GSM, a pair of calls can be merged into a conference. In XMPP
            and MSN, you can create a new chatroom, or upgrade one 1-1 channel
            into a chatroom; however, on these protocols, it is also possible
            to fake GSM-style merging by upgrading the first channel, then
            inviting the targets of all the other channels into it.</p>
        </tp:rationale>

        <p>If possible, the <tp:member-ref>Channels</tp:member-ref>' states SHOULD
          NOT be altered by merging them into a conference. However, depending on
          the protocol, the Channels MAY be placed in a "frozen" state by placing
          them in this property's value or by calling
          <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface"
            >MergeableConference.DRAFT.Merge</tp:dbus-ref> on them.
          <strong>[FIXME: there's nothing in RequestableChannelClasses yet
            to say what will happen, see #24906 comment 6]</strong></p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>In Jingle, nothing special will happen to merged calls. UIs MAY
            automatically place calls on hold before merging them, if that is
            the desired behaviour; this SHOULD always work. Not doing
            an implicit hold/unhold seems to preserve least-astonishment.</p>

          <p><strong>[FIXME: check whether ring supports faking Hold on both
              channels, as it probably should: see #24906 comment 6]</strong>
          </p>

          <p>In GSM, the calls that are merged go into a state similar to
            Hold, but they cannot be unheld, only split from the conference
            call using <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy"
              >Channel.Interface.Splittable.DRAFT.Split</tp:dbus-ref>.</p>
        </tp:rationale>

        <p>Depending on the protocol, it might be signalled to remote users
          that this channel is a continuation of all the requested channels,
          or that it is only a continuation of the first channel in the
          list.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>In MSN, the conference steals the underlying switchboard (protocol
            construct) from one of its component channels, so the conference
            appears to remote users to be a continuation of that channel and no
            other. The connection manager has to make some arbitrary choice, so
            we arbitrarily mandate that it SHOULD choose the first channel in
            the list as the one to continue.</p>
        </tp:rationale>

        <p>This property is immutable.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="InitialInviteeHandles"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Initial_Invitee_Handles"
      access="read" type="au" tp:type="Contact_Handle[]">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>A list of additional contacts invited to this conference when it
          was created.</p>

        <p>This property SHOULD be requestable, and appear in the allowed
          properties in <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.Requests"
            >RequestableChannelClasses</tp:dbus-ref>, in all connection
          managers that can implement its semantics (in practice, this is
          likely to mean exactly those connection managers where
          <tp:member-ref>SupportsNonMerges</tp:member-ref> will be true).</p>

        <p>If included in a request, the given contacts are automatically
          invited into the new channel, as if they had been added with
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface"
            >Group.AddMembers</tp:dbus-ref>(InitialInviteeHandles,
          <tp:member-ref>InvitationMessage</tp:member-ref> immediately after
          the channel was created.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>This is a simple convenience API for the common case that a UI
            upgrades a 1-1 chat to a multi-user chat solely in order to invite
            someone else to participate.</p>
        </tp:rationale>

        <p>At most one of InitialInviteeHandles and InitialInviteeIDs may
          appear in each request.</p>

        <p>If the local user was not the initiator of this channel, the
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface"
            >Group.SelfHandle</tp:dbus-ref> SHOULD appear in the value of this
          property, together with any other contacts invited at the same time
          (if that information is known).</p>

        <p>This property is immutable.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="InitialInviteeIDs"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Initial_Invitee_IDs"
      access="read" type="as">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>A list of additional contacts invited to this conference when it
          was created.</p>

        <p>This property SHOULD be requestable, as an alternative to
          <tp:member-ref>InitialInviteeHandles</tp:member-ref>. Its semantics
          are the same, except that it takes a list of the string
          representations of contact handles.</p>

        <p>At most one of InitialInviteeHandles and InitialInviteeIDs may
          appear in each request.</p>

        <p>When a channel is created, the values of InitialInviteeHandles and
          InitialInviteeIDs MUST correspond to each other.</p>

        <p>This property is immutable.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="InvitationMessage" tp:name-for-bindings="Invitation_Message"
      access="read" type="s">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The message that was sent to the
          <tp:member-ref>InitialInviteeHandles</tp:member-ref> when they were
          invited.</p>

        <p>This property SHOULD be requestable, and appear in the allowed
          properties in <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.Requests"
            >RequestableChannelClasses</tp:dbus-ref>, in protocols where
          invitations can have an accompanying text message.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>This allows invitations with a message to be sent when using
            <tp:member-ref>InitialInviteeHandles</tp:member-ref> or
            <tp:member-ref>InitialInviteeIDs</tp:member-ref>.</p>
        </tp:rationale>

        <p>If the local user was not the initiator of this channel, the
          message with which they were invited (if any) SHOULD appear in the
          value of this property.</p>

        <p>This property is immutable.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="SupportsNonMerges"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Supports_Non_Merges"
      access="read" type="b">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p><strong>[FIXME: needs a better name; or perhaps it could be implied
            by InitialInviteeHandles being requestable in XMPP/MSN but not in
            GSM?]</strong></p>

        <p>If true, requests with <tp:member-ref>InitialChannels</tp:member-ref>
          omitted, empty, or one element long should be expected to succeed.</p>

        <p>This property SHOULD appear in <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.Requests"
              >RequestableChannelClasses</tp:dbus-ref> for
          conference channels if and only if its value on those channels will
          be true.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>Putting this in <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.Requests"
              >RequestableChannelClasses</tp:dbus-ref> means clients can find
            out whether their request will succeed early enough to do
            something about it.</p>

          <p>In XMPP, you can request a channel of type ROOM without
            incorporating any 1-1 chats at all - indeed, this is the normal
            way to do it - or as a continuation of a single 1-1 chat, and then
            invite other people in later.</p>

          <p>The sense of this property is a bit awkward, but it avoids making it
            an anti-capability. If the sense were inverted, then its presence in
            RequestableChannelClasses would imply that the protocol <em>lacks</em>
            a feature; as it stands, it is additive. (Contrast with
            <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Type.StreamedMedia"
              >ImmutableStreams</tp:dbus-ref>, which is the wrong way around for
            backwards-compatibility reasons.)</p>
        </tp:rationale>

        <p>If false, <tp:member-ref>InitialChannels</tp:member-ref> SHOULD be
          supplied in all requests for this channel class, and contain at least
          two channels. Requests where this requirement is not met SHOULD fail
          with NotImplemented.
        </p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>In GSM, you can only make a conference call by merging at least
            two channels.
            <strong>[FIXME: the CM could conceivably fake it, but that would be
              rather nasty]</strong>
          </p>
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

  </interface>
</node>
