<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Channel_Bundle"
  xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright>Copyright (C) 2008 Collabora Ltd.</tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright>Copyright (C) 2008 Nokia Corporation</tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.
</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.ChannelBundle.DRAFT"
    tp:causes-havoc="experimental">
    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>A group of related channels, which should all be dispatched to the
        same handler if possible.</p>

      <p>Bundles currently have no functionality of their own, so clients
        SHOULD NOT examine this interface, but should instead treat the
        bundle object-path as an opaque identifier. If more functionality is
        added to bundles in future, this interface will be used for capability
        discovery.</p>

      <p>The lifetime of a bundle is defined by its component channels -
        as long as one or more channels whose Bundle property is <em>B</em>
        exist, the bundle <em>B</em> will also exist.</p>
    </tp:docstring>

    <property name="Interfaces" tp:name-for-bindings="Interfaces"
      type="as" access="read" tp:type="DBus_Interface[]">
      <tp:docstring>
        A list of the extra interfaces provided by this channel bundle.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
