<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Channel_Interface_Anonymity"
  xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">

  <tp:copyright>Copyright © 2008-2010 Nokia Corporation</tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright>Copyright © 2010 Collabora Ltd.</tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
      modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
      License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
      version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

    <p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
      but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
      MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
      Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

    <p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
      License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
      Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA
      02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>

  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface.Anonymity">
    <tp:added version="0.19.7">(as stable API)</tp:added>

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>Interface for requesting the anonymity modes of a channel
        (as defined in <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy"
          >Connection.Interface.Anonymity</tp:dbus-ref>).</p>
    </tp:docstring>

    <property name="AnonymityModes" type="u" tp:type="Anonymity_Mode_Flags"
      access="read" tp:name-for-bindings="Anonymity_Modes">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        The list of initially requested anonymity modes on the channel.  This
        MUST NOT change, and is Requestable.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="AnonymityMandatory" type="b" access="read"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Anonymity_Mandatory">
      <tp:docstring>
        Whether or not the anonymity settings are required for this channel.
        This MUST NOT change, and is Requestable.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="AnonymousID" type="s" access="read"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Anonymous_ID">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>This is the ID that the remote user of the channel MAY see
        (assuming there's a single ID).  For example, for SIP connections
        where the From address has been scrambled by the CM, the scrambled
        address would be available here for the client to see.  This is
        completely optional, and MAY be an empty string ("") in
        cases where anonymity modes are not set, or the CM doesn't know
        what the remote contact will see, or any other case where this
        doesn't make sense.</p>

        <p>This MAY change over the lifetime of the channel, and SHOULD NOT
        be used with the Request interface.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
