<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Channel_Interface_SMS"
  xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright>Copyright © 2008–2010 Nokia Corporation</tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright>Copyright © 2010 Collabora Ltd.</tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Library General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.
  </tp:license>

  <interface
    name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface.SMS">
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Type.Text"/>
    <tp:added version='0.19.12'>Imported from
      rtcom-telepathy-glib, with the unused properties removed and the
      documentation tidied up.</tp:added>

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>This interface contains SMS-specific properties for text channels.
        This currently only includes whether the SMSes received on the channel
        should be displayed immediately to the user, without prompting.</p>

      <h4>Handler filters</h4>

      <p>A handler for class 0 SMSes should advertise the following filter:</p>

      <blockquote><code>
{ ...<tp:dbus-ref namespace='ofdT.Channel'>ChannelType</tp:dbus-ref>:
      ...<tp:dbus-ref namespace='ofdT.Channel.Type'>Text</tp:dbus-ref>,<br/>
  ...<tp:dbus-ref namespace='ofdT.Channel'>TargetHandleType</tp:dbus-ref>:
      <tp:type>Handle_Type</tp:type>_Contact,<br/>
  ...<tp:dbus-ref namespace='ofdT.Channel.Interface'>SMS.Flash</tp:dbus-ref>:
      True,<br/>
}</code></blockquote>

      <p>It should also set its <tp:dbus-ref
        namespace='ofdT.Client.Handler'>BypassApproval</tp:dbus-ref> property
        to <code>True</code>, so that it is invoked immediately for new
        channels.</p>
    </tp:docstring>

    <property name="Flash" tp:name-for-bindings="Flash"
      type="b" access="read" >
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>If <code>True</code>, then this channel is exclusively for
          receiving class 0 SMSes (and no SMSes can be sent using <tp:dbus-ref
          namespace='ofdT.Channel.Interface.Messages'>SendMessage</tp:dbus-ref>
          on this channel). If <code>False</code>, no incoming class 0 SMSes
          will appear on this channel.</p>

        <p>This property is immutable (cannot change), and therefore SHOULD
          appear wherever immutable properties are reported, e.g. <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="ofdT.Connection.Interface.Requests"
          >NewChannels</tp:dbus-ref> signals.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>Class 0 SMSes should be displayed immediately to the user, and
            need not be saved to the device memory unless the user explicitly
            chooses to do so. This is unlike “normal”, class 1 SMSes, which
            must be stored, but need not be shown immediately in their entirity
            to the user.</p>

          <p>Separating class 0 SMSes into their own channel with this
            immutable property allows them to be dispatched to a different
            <tp:dbus-ref namespace='ofdT.Client'>Handler</tp:dbus-ref>—which
            would include this property in its <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace='ofdT.Client.Handler'
            >HandlerChannelFilter</tp:dbus-ref>—avoiding the normal Text
            channel handler having to decide for each message whether it should
            be displayed to the user immediately or handled normally.</p>

          <p>Currently, no mechanism is defined for <em>sending</em> class 0
            SMSes. It seems reasonable to support specifying the class of an
            outgoing SMS in its header <tp:type>Message_Part</tp:type>, rather
            than requiring the UI to request a special channel for such SMSes;
            hence, we define here that channels with Flash set to
            <code>True</code> are read-only.</p>
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>
  </interface>
</node>
