<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Channel_Type_Text" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2005, 2006 Collabora Limited </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2005, 2006 Nokia Corporation </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2006 INdT </tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Type.Text">
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel"/>

    <tp:simple-type name="Message_ID" type="u">
      <tp:docstring>
        A unique-per-channel identifier for an incoming message. These
        SHOULD be allocated in a way that minimizes collisions (in particular,
        message IDs SHOULD NOT be re-used until all of the 32-bit integer
        space has already been used).
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:simple-type>

    <tp:struct name="Pending_Text_Message" array-name="Pending_Text_Message_List">
      <tp:docstring>A struct (message ID, timestamp in seconds since
        1970-01-01 00:00 UTC, sender's handle, message type, flags, text)
        representing a pending text message, as returned by ListPendingMessages
        on the Text channel type. The arguments of the Received signal
        also match this struct's signature.</tp:docstring>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Message_ID" name="Identifier"/>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Unix_Timestamp" name="Unix_Timestamp"/>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Contact_Handle" name="Sender"/>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Channel_Text_Message_Type"
                 name="Message_Type"/>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Channel_Text_Message_Flags" name="Flags"/>
      <tp:member type="s" name="Text"/>
    </tp:struct>

    <method name="AcknowledgePendingMessages">
      <arg direction="in" name="ids" type="au" tp:type="Message_ID[]">
        <tp:docstring>
          The IDs of the messages to acknowledge
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Inform the channel that you have handled messages by displaying them to
        the user (or equivalent), so they can be removed from the pending queue.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidArgument">
          <tp:docstring>
            A given message ID was not found, so no action was taken
          </tp:docstring>
        </tp:error>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <method name="GetMessageTypes">
      <arg direction="out" type="au" tp:type="Channel_Text_Message_Type[]">
        <tp:docstring>
          An array of integer message types (ChannelTextMessageType)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Return an array indicating which types of message may be sent on this
        channel.
      </tp:docstring>
    </method>

    <method name="ListPendingMessages">
      <arg direction="in" name="clear" type="b">
        <tp:docstring>
          If true, behave as if AcknowledgePendingMessages had also been
          called.
        </tp:docstring>
        <tp:deprecated since="0.17.3">
          Setting this to true is NOT RECOMMENDED for clients that
          have some sort of persistent message storage - clients SHOULD only
          acknowledge messages after they have actually stored them, which is
          impossible if this flag is true.</tp:deprecated>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="a(uuuuus)" tp:type="Pending_Text_Message[]">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          An array of structs representing the pending queue. Each contains:
          <ul>
            <li>a numeric identifier</li>
            <li>a Unix timestamp indicating when the message was received</li>
            <li>the contact handle for the contact who sent the message</li>
            <li>the message type, taken from ChannelTextMessageType</li>
            <li>the bitwise-OR of the message flags from ChannelTextMessageFlags</li>
            <li>the text of the message</li>
          </ul>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        List the messages currently in the pending queue, and optionally
        remove then all.
      </tp:docstring>
    </method>

    <signal name="LostMessage">
      <tp:docstring>
        This signal is emitted to indicate that an incoming message was
        not able to be stored and forwarded by the connection manager
        due to lack of memory.
      </tp:docstring>
    </signal>

    <signal name="Received">
      <arg name="id" type="u">
        <tp:docstring>
          A numeric identifier for acknowledging the message
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="timestamp" type="u" tp:type="Unix_Timestamp">
        <tp:docstring>
          A Unix timestamp indicating when the message was received
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="sender" type="u" tp:type="Contact_Handle">
        <tp:docstring>
          The handle of the contact who sent the message
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="type" type="u" tp:type="Channel_Text_Message_Type">
        <tp:docstring>
          The type of the message (normal, action, notice, etc.)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="flags" type="u" tp:type="Channel_Text_Message_Flags">
        <tp:docstring>
          A bitwise OR of the message flags
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="text" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          The text of the message
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Signals that a message with the given id, timestamp, sender, type
        and text has been received on this channel. Applications that catch
        this signal and reliably inform the user of the message should
        acknowledge that they have dealt with the message with the
        AcknowledgePendingMessage method.
      </tp:docstring>
    </signal>

    <method name="Send">
      <arg direction="in" name="type" type="u" tp:type="Channel_Text_Message_Type">
        <tp:docstring>
          An integer indicating the type of the message
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="text" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          The message to send
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Request that a message be sent on this channel. When the message has
        been submitted for delivery, this method will return and the Sent
        signal will be emitted. If the message cannot be submitted for
        delivery, the method returns an error and no signal is emitted.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.Disconnected"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidArgument"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.PermissionDenied"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <tp:enum name="Channel_Text_Send_Error" type="u">
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Unknown" value="0">
        <tp:docstring>
        An unknown error occurred
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Offline" value="1">
        <tp:docstring>
        The requested contact was offline
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Invalid_Contact" value="2">
        <tp:docstring>
        The requested contact is not valid
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Permission_Denied" value="3">
        <tp:docstring>
        The user does not have permission to speak on this channel
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Too_Long" value="4">
        <tp:docstring>
        The outgoing message was too long and was rejected by the server
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Not_Implemented" value="5">
        <tp:docstring>
        The channel doesn't support sending text messages to the requested
        contact
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
    </tp:enum>

    <signal name="SendError">
      <arg name="error" type="u" tp:type="Channel_Text_Send_Error">
        <tp:docstring>
          The error that occurred
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="timestamp" type="u" tp:type="Unix_Timestamp">
        <tp:docstring>
          The Unix timestamp indicating when the message was sent
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="type" type="u" tp:type="Channel_Text_Message_Type">
        <tp:docstring>
          The message type
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="text" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          The text of the message
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Signals that an outgoing message has failed to send. The error
          will be one of the values from ChannelTextSendError.</p>

        <p>This signal should only be emitted for messages for which
          Sent has already been emitted and Send has already returned
          success.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:changed version="0.17.3">older spec versions claimed that SendError
        was emitted <em>instead of</em> Sent, rather than <em>in addition
        to</em> Sent. However, the 0.17.3+ semantics were what we'd always
        actually implemented.</tp:changed>
    </signal>

    <signal name="Sent">
      <arg name="timestamp" type="u" tp:type="Unix_Timestamp">
        <tp:docstring>
          Unix timestamp indicating when the message was sent
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="type" type="u" tp:type="Channel_Text_Message_Type">
        <tp:docstring>
          The message type (normal, action, notice, etc) from
          ChannelTextMessageType
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="text" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          The text of the message
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Signals that a message has been submitted for sending.
      </tp:docstring>
    </signal>

    <tp:enum name="Channel_Text_Message_Type" type="u">
      <tp:docstring>
        The type of message.
      </tp:docstring>

      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Normal" value="0">
        <tp:docstring>
        An ordinary chat message. Unknown types SHOULD be treated like this.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>

      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Action" value="1">
        <tp:docstring>
        An action which might be presented to the user as
        "* &lt;sender&gt; &lt;action&gt;", such as an IRC CTCP
        ACTION (typically selected by the "/me" command). For example, the
        text of the message might be "drinks more coffee".
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>

      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Notice" value="2">
        <tp:docstring>
        A one-off or automated message not necessarily expecting a reply
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>

      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Auto_Reply" value="3">
        <tp:docstring>
        An automatically-generated reply message.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>

      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Delivery_Report" value="4">
        <tp:docstring>
          This message type MUST NOT appear unless the channel supports the
          DeliveryReporting interface. The message MUST be as defined by
          the DeliveryReporting interface.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
    </tp:enum>

    <tp:flags name="Channel_Text_Message_Flags" value-prefix="Channel_Text_Message_Flag" type="u">
      <tp:flag suffix="Truncated" value="1">
        <tp:docstring>
        The incoming message was truncated to a shorter length by the
        server or the connection manager.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>

      <tp:flag suffix="Non_Text_Content" value="2">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          <p>The incoming message contained non-text content which cannot be
            represented by this interface, but has been signalled
            in the Messages interface.</p>

          <p>Connection managers SHOULD only set this flag if the non-text
            content appears to be relatively significant (exactly how
            significant is up to the implementor). The intention is that
            if this flag is set, clients using this interface SHOULD inform
            the user that part of the message was not understood.</p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
    </tp:flags>

    <tp:property name="anonymous" type="b">
      <tp:docstring>
      True if people may join the channel without other members being made
      aware of their identity.
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>
    <tp:property name="invite-only" type="b">
      <tp:docstring>
      True if people may not join the channel until they have been invited.
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>
    <tp:property name="limit" type="u">
      <tp:docstring>
      The limit to the number of members, if limited is true.
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>
    <tp:property name="limited" type="b">
      <tp:docstring>
      True if there is a limit to the number of channel members.
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>
    <tp:property name="moderated" type="b">
      <tp:docstring>
      True if channel membership is not sufficient to allow participation.
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>
    <tp:property name="name" type="s">
      <tp:docstring>
      A human-visible name for the channel, if it differs from the string
      version of the channel's handle.
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>
    <tp:property name="description" type="s">
      <tp:docstring>
      A human-readable description of the channel's overall purpose.
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>
    <tp:property name="password" type="s">
      <tp:docstring>
      The password required to enter the channel if password-required is true.
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>
    <tp:property name="password-required" type="b">
      <tp:docstring>
      True if a password must be provided to enter the channel.
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>
    <tp:property name="persistent" type="b">
      <tp:docstring>
      True if the channel will remain in existence on the server after all
      members have left it.
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>
    <tp:property name="private" type="b">
      <tp:docstring>
      True if the channel is not visible to non-members.
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>
    <tp:property name="subject" type="s">
      <tp:docstring>
      A human-readable description of the current subject of conversation in
      the channel, similar to /topic in IRC.
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>
    <tp:property name="subject-contact" type="u" tp:type="Contact_Handle">
      <tp:docstring>
      A contact handle representing who last modified the subject, or 0
      if it isn't known.
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>
    <tp:property name="subject-timestamp" type="u" tp:type="Unix_Timestamp">
      <tp:docstring>
      A unix timestamp indicating when the subject was last modified.
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>A channel type for sending and receiving messages in plain text,
        with no formatting. In future specifications, channels for sending
        and receiving messages that can be reduced to plain text (i.e.
        formatted text) should also have this type.</p>

      <p>When a message is received, an identifier is assigned and a
        Received signal emitted, and the message placed in a pending queue
        which can be inspected with ListPendingMessages. A client which has
        handled the message by showing it to the user (or equivalent) should
        acknowledge the receipt using the AcknowledgePendingMessage method,
        and the message will then be removed from the pending queue. Numeric
        identifiers for received messages may be reused over the lifetime of
        the channel.</p>

      <p>Each message has an associated 'type' value, which should be one
        of the values allowed by ChannelTextMessageType.</p>

      <p>Each message also has a flags value, which is a bitwise OR of the
        flags given in ChannelTextMessageFlags.</p>

      <p>Sending messages can be requested using the Send method, which will
        return successfully and emit the Sent signal when the message has
        been delivered to the server, or return an error with no signal
        emission if there is a failure. If a message is sent but delivery
        of the message later fails, this is indicated with the SendError
        signal.</p>

      <p>On protocols where additional contacts cannot be invited into
        a one-to-one chat, or where a one-to-one chat is just a series of
        individual personal messages rather than being represented by some
        object on the server (i.e. most protocols), one-to-one chats should be
        represented by a Text channel with handle type CONTACT.</p>

      <p>Named chat rooms whose identity can be saved and used again later
        (IRC channels, Jabber MUCs) are expected to be represented by Text
        channels with handle type ROOM and the Group interface; they should
        usually also have the Properties interface.</p>

      <p>Unnamed, transient chat rooms defined only by their members (e.g. on
        MSN) are expected to be represented by Text channels with handle type
        0, handle 0, the Group interface, and optionally the Properties
        interface.</p>

      <p>On protocols where a conversation with a user is actually just
        a nameless chat room starting with exactly two members, to which
        more members can be invited, calling RequestChannel with type Text
        and handle type CONTACT should continue to succeed, but may return
        a channel with handle type 0, handle 0, the group interface,
        and the local and remote contacts in its members.</p>
    </tp:docstring>
  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
