<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Channel_Interface_Media_Signalling_Future"
  xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright> Copyright © 2009 Collabora Limited </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright © 2009 Nokia Corporation </tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
      modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
      License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
      version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

    <p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
      but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
      MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
      Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

    <p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
      License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
      Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301,
      USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface.MediaSignalling.FUTURE">
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel"/>
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Type.StreamedMedia"/>
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface.MediaSignalling"/>

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>This interface contains functionality which we intend to incorporate
        into the <tp:dbus-ref
          namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Channel.Interface.MediaSignalling</tp:dbus-ref>
        interface in future. It should be considered to be conceptually part
        of the core MediaSignalling interface, but without API or ABI
        guarantees.</p>

      <tp:rationale>
        <p>The rationale is the same as for <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Channel.FUTURE</tp:dbus-ref>.</p>
      </tp:rationale>
    </tp:docstring>

    <property name="ICETransportAvailable"
      tp:name-for-bindings="ICE_Transport_Available"
      type="b" access="read">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>True if this channel supports the use of the ICE-UDP transport
          (<a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0176.html">XEP-0176</a>,
          <a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-mmusic-ice">ICE RFC
            draft)</a>. Various other transports have boolean properties
          that work in the same way as this one, so this description covers
          all such transports.</p>

        <p>This property is immutable (cannot change), and therefore SHOULD
          appear wherever immutable properties are reported, e.g. <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.Requests">NewChannels</tp:dbus-ref>
          signals.</p>

        <p>Connection managers capable of signalling streamed media calls to
          contacts SHOULD include the properties representing all supported
          transports in the allowed properties list of the channel class
          in <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.Requests">RequestableChannelClasses</tp:dbus-ref>
          that advertises support for streamed media channels.</p>

        <p>Similarly, connection managers that support the <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface">ContactCapabilities.DRAFT</tp:dbus-ref>
          interface SHOULD include all supported transports in the allowed
          properties list of the channel class that advertises a contact's
          ability to receive streamed media calls.</p>

        <p>Clients SHOULD NOT pass ICETransportAvailable and similar
          properties to <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.Requests">EnsureChannel</tp:dbus-ref>
          or similar functions. If they do, the connection manager MUST
          accept and ignore any such property that is in the allowed properties
          list.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>There is currently no way for clients to influence the choice
            of transport: in general, a client making a call can't know the
            capabilities of the streaming implementation, or even which
            streaming implementation will be used (channels will often be
            requested by an address book or similar application that will not
            handle the channel itself).</p>

          <p>If a mechanism for transport negotiation is added, it should be
            something that happens after the request, but before calling
            <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Media.SessionHandler.Ready</tp:dbus-ref>,
            so that it is the streaming implementation that chooses the
            transport, rather than the requesting client.</p>
        </tp:rationale>

        <p>Clients that are able to receive calls with particular transports
          MUST include the following filters if calling <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.ContactCapabilities.DRAFT">SetSelfCapabilities</tp:dbus-ref>
          (clients of a <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">ChannelDispatcher</tp:dbus-ref>
          SHOULD instead arrange for the ChannelDispatcher to do this,
          by including the filters in their <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Client.Handler">HandlerChannelFilter</tp:dbus-ref>
          properties):</p>

        <ul>
          <li>{ ChannelType = StreamedMedia, ICETransportAvailable = true }
            if the ICE transport is supported</li>
          <li>{ ChannelType = StreamedMedia, RawUDPTransportAvailable = true }
            if the raw UDP transport is supported</li>
          <li>... and so on, one filter per available transport.</li>
        </ul>

        <p>Connection managers MAY use this information to adjust the
          transports for which they advertise support to other contacts.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>In particular, in XMPP, the connection manager will not be
            callable unless a client has told it to advertise support for
            at least one transport.</p>
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="RawUDPTransportAvailable"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Raw_UDP_Transport_Available"
      type="b" access="read">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The same as <tp:member-ref>ICETransportAvailable</tp:member-ref>,
          but for raw UDP streaming as described by <a
            href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0177.html">XEP-0177</a>.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="GTalkP2PTransportAvailable"
      tp:name-for-bindings="GTalk_P2P_Transport_Available"
      type="b" access="read">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The same as <tp:member-ref>ICETransportAvailable</tp:member-ref>,
          but for the variant of ICE used by the Google Talk peer-to-peer
          connectivity establishment mechanism (as implemented in libjingle
          0.3).</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="WLM85TransportAvailable"
      tp:name-for-bindings="WLM_8_5_Transport_Available"
      type="b" access="read">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The same as <tp:member-ref>ICETransportAvailable</tp:member-ref>,
          but for the transport implemented by Windows Live Messenger 8.5 or
          later (which resembles ICE draft 6).</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="WLM2009TransportAvailable"
      tp:name-for-bindings="WLM_2009_Transport_Available"
      type="b" access="read">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The same as <tp:member-ref>ICETransportAvailable</tp:member-ref>,
          but for the transport implemented by Windows Live Messenger 2009
          or later (which resembles ICE draft 19).</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

  </interface>
</node>
