<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Channel_Handler" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright>Copyright (C) 2007-2008 Collabora Limited</tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.ChannelHandler">

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>An interface exported by client applications which are able to
        handle incoming channels.</p>
    </tp:docstring>
    <tp:added version="0.17.0"/>

    <method name="HandleChannel" tp:name-for-bindings="Handle_Channel">
      <tp:docstring>
        Called when a channel handler should handle a new channel.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:added version="0.17.0"/>

      <arg direction="in" type="s" name="Bus_Name" tp:type="DBus_Bus_Name">
        <tp:docstring>
          The bus name of the connection and channel
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg direction="in" type="o" name="Connection">
        <tp:docstring>
          The object-path of the connection that owns the channel
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg direction="in" type="s" tp:type="DBus_Interface" name="Channel_Type">
        <tp:docstring>
          The channel type
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg direction="in" type="o" name="Channel">
        <tp:docstring>
          The object-path of the channel
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg direction="in" type="u" tp:type="Handle_Type" name="Handle_Type">
        <tp:docstring>The type of the handle that the channel communicates
          with, or 0 if there is no associated handle</tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg direction="in" type="u" tp:type="Handle" name="Handle">
        <tp:docstring>The handle that the channel communicates with,
          or 0 if there is no associated handle</tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <!-- FIXME: possible errors? -->
    </method>

  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->

