<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Channel_Type_Streamed_Media" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2005-2008 Collabora Limited </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2005-2008 Nokia Corporation </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2006 INdT </tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Type.StreamedMedia">
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel"/>
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface.Group"/>

    <tp:enum name="Media_Stream_Type" type="u">
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Audio" value="0">
        <tp:docstring>An audio stream</tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Video" value="1">
        <tp:docstring>A video stream</tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
    </tp:enum>

    <tp:enum name="Media_Stream_State" type="u">
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Disconnected" value="0">
        <tp:docstring>The stream is disconnected.</tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Connecting" value="1">
        <tp:docstring>The stream is trying to connect.</tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Connected" value="2">
        <tp:docstring>The stream is connected.</tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
    </tp:enum>

    <tp:enum name="Media_Stream_Direction" type="u">
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="None" value="0">
        <tp:docstring>Media are not being sent or received</tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Send" value="1">
        <tp:docstring>Media are being sent, but not received</tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Receive" value="2">
        <tp:docstring>Media are being received, but not sent</tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Bidirectional" value="3">
        <tp:docstring>Media are being sent and received</tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
    </tp:enum>

    <tp:flags name="Media_Stream_Pending_Send" value-prefix="Media_Stream_Pending" type="u">
      <tp:flag suffix="Local_Send" value="1">
        <tp:docstring>
            The local user has been asked to send media by the remote user.
            Call RequestStreamDirection to indicate whether or not this is
            acceptable.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
      <tp:flag suffix="Remote_Send" value="2">
        <tp:docstring>
            The remote user has been asked to send media by the local user.
            The StreamDirectionChanged signal will be emitted when the remote
            user accepts or rejects this change.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
    </tp:flags>

    <tp:struct name="Media_Stream_Info" array-name="Media_Stream_Info_List">
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Stream_ID" name="Identifier"/>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Contact_Handle" name="Contact"/>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Media_Stream_Type" name="Type"/>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Media_Stream_State" name="State"/>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Media_Stream_Direction" name="Direction"/>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Media_Stream_Pending_Send"
        name="Pending_Send_Flags"/>
    </tp:struct>

    <tp:simple-type name="Stream_ID" type="u"/>

    <method name="ListStreams">
      <arg direction="out" type="a(uuuuuu)" tp:type="Media_Stream_Info[]">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          An array of structs containing:
          <ul>
          <li>the stream identifier</li>
          <li>the contact handle who the stream is with (or 0 if the stream
            represents more than a single member)</li>
          <li>the type of the stream</li>
          <li>the current stream state</li>
          <li>the current direction of the stream</li>
          <li>the current pending send flags</li>
          </ul>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Returns an array of structs representing the streams currently active
        within this channel. Each stream is identified by an unsigned integer
        which is unique for each stream within the channel.
      </tp:docstring>
    </method>

    <method name="RemoveStreams">
      <arg direction="in" name="streams" type="au" tp:type="Stream_ID[]">
        <tp:docstring>
          An array of stream identifiers (as defined in ListStreams)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Request that the given streams are removed.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidArgument">
          A stream identifier is unknown
        </tp:error>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <method name="RequestStreamDirection">
      <arg direction="in" name="stream_id" type="u">
        <tp:docstring>
          The stream identifier (as defined in ListStreams)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="stream_direction" type="u" tp:type="Media_Stream_Direction">
        <tp:docstring>
          The desired stream direction (a value of MediaStreamDirection)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Request a change in the direction of an existing stream. In particular,
        this might be useful to stop sending media of a particular type,
        or inform the peer that you are no longer using media that is being
        sent to you.</p>

        <p>Depending on the protocol, streams which are no longer sending in
        either direction should be removed and a StreamRemoved signal emitted.
        Some direction changes can be enforced locally (for example,
        BIDIRECTIONAL -&gt; RECEIVE can be achieved by merely stopping sending),
        others may not be possible on some protocols, and some need agreement
        from the remote end. In this case, the MEDIA_STREAM_PENDING_REMOTE_SEND
        flag will be set in the StreamDirectionChanged signal, and the signal
        emitted again without the flag to indicate the resulting direction when
        the remote end has accepted or rejected the change.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidArgument">
          A stream identifier is unknown
        </tp:error>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable">
          The requested direction is not available on this stream
        </tp:error>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <method name="RequestStreams">
      <arg direction="in" name="contact_handle" type="u" tp:type="Contact_Handle">
        <tp:docstring>
          A contact handle with whom to establish the streams
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="types" type="au" tp:type="Media_Stream_Type[]">
        <tp:docstring>
          An array of stream types (values of MediaStreamType)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="a(uuuuuu)" tp:type="Media_Stream_Info[]">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          An array of structs (in the same order as the given stream types)
          containing:
          <ul>
            <li>the stream identifier</li>
            <li>the contact handle who the stream is with (or 0 if the stream
              represents more than a single member)</li>
            <li>the type of the stream</li>
            <li>the current stream state</li>
            <li>the current direction of the stream</li>
            <li>the current pending send flags</li>
          </ul>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Request that streams be established to exchange the given types of
        media with the given member. In general this will try and establish a
        bidirectional stream, but on some protocols it may not be possible to
        indicate to the peer that you would like to receive media, so a
        send-only stream will be created initially. In the cases where the
        stream requires remote agreement (eg you wish to receive media from
        them), the StreamDirectionChanged signal will be emitted with the
        MEDIA_STREAM_PENDING_REMOTE_SEND flag set, and the signal emitted again
        with the flag cleared when the remote end has replied.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:changed version="0.17.2">
        <p>It is valid to use a handle which is neither
          a current nor pending member in this channel's Group interface. If
          so, that handle will be added to the remote-pending set only when
          an attempt has actually been made to contact them. For further
          call-state notification, use the CallState interface, if
          supported. This usage was not allowed in spec versions below
          0.17.2.</p>
      </tp:changed>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidHandle"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidArgument">
          A stream type given is invalid
        </tp:error>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable">
          That contact is not able to do this stream type
        </tp:error>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <signal name="StreamAdded">
      <arg name="stream_id" type="u">
        <tp:docstring>
          The stream identifier (as defined in ListStreams)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="contact_handle" type="u" tp:type="Contact_Handle">
        <tp:docstring>
          The contact handle who the stream is with (or 0 if it
          represents more than a single member)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="stream_type" type="u" tp:type="Media_Stream_Type">
        <tp:docstring>
          The stream type (a value from MediaStreamType)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Emitted when a new stream has been added to this channel.
      </tp:docstring>
    </signal>

    <signal name="StreamDirectionChanged">
      <arg name="stream_id" type="u">
        <tp:docstring>
        The stream identifier (as defined in ListStreams)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="stream_direction" type="u" tp:type="Media_Stream_Direction">
        <tp:docstring>
        The new stream direction (as defined in ListStreams)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="pending_flags" type="u" tp:type="Media_Stream_Pending_Send">
        <tp:docstring>
        The new pending send flags (as defined in ListStreams)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Emitted when the direction or pending flags of a stream are changed. If
        the MEDIA_STREAM_PENDING_LOCAL_SEND flag is set, the remote user has
        requested that we begin sending on this stream. RequestStreamDirection
        should be called to indicate whether or not this change is acceptable.
      </tp:docstring>
    </signal>

    <signal name="StreamError">
      <arg name="stream_id" type="u">
        <tp:docstring>
        The stream identifier (as defined in ListStreams)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="errno" type="u">
        <tp:docstring>
          A stream error number, one of the values of MediaStreamError
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="message" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          A string describing the error (for debugging purposes only)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Emitted when a stream encounters an error.
      </tp:docstring>
    </signal>

    <signal name="StreamRemoved">
      <arg name="stream_id" type="u">
        <tp:docstring>
        stream_id - the stream identifier (as defined in ListStreams)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Emitted when a stream has been removed from this channel.
      </tp:docstring>
    </signal>

    <signal name="StreamStateChanged">
      <arg name="stream_id" type="u">
        <tp:docstring>
          The stream identifier (as defined in ListStreams)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="stream_state" type="u" tp:type="Media_Stream_State">
        <tp:docstring>
          The new stream state (as defined in ListStreams)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Emitted when a member's stream's state changes.
      </tp:docstring>
    </signal>

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>A channel that can send and receive streamed media such as audio or video.
    Provides a number of methods for listing and requesting new streams, and
    signals to indicate when streams have been added, removed and changed
    status.</p>

      <p>Channels of this type are expected to provide the Group interface
        and be "anonymous" (have no associated handle). To make a media call
        to a contact, clients should request a new, empty streamed media
        channel, then call AddMembers to add the contact to the channel.
        The local user should be in the group's members, while the contact
        should be absent from the channel until a call is made, appear in
        "remote pending" from when the call is attempted until the call is
        accepted, then move to the group's members.</p>

      <p>Similarly, incoming calls should be signalled as having handle type 0
        and handle 0. The remote contact should be in the group's members,
        with the local user in the "local pending" members; to accept the
        call, AddMembers can be used to move the local user to the
        group's members.</p>

    <p>In general this should be used in conjunction with the MediaSignalling
    interface to exchange connection candidates and codec choices with
    whichever component is responsible for the streams. However, in certain
    applications where no candidate exchange is necessary (eg the streams are
    handled by specialised hardware which is controlled directly by the
    connection manager), the signalling interface can be omitted and this
    channel type used simply to control the streams.</p>
    </tp:docstring>

    <tp:flags name="Channel_Media_Capabilities" value-prefix="Channel_Media_Capability" type="u">
      <tp:docstring>
        The channel-type-specific capability flags used for
        Channel.Type.StreamedMedia in the Connection.Interface.Capabilities
        interface.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:flag suffix="Audio" value="1">
        <tp:docstring>
          The handle is capable of using audio streams within a media channel.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
      <tp:flag suffix="Video" value="2">
        <tp:docstring>
          The handle is capable of using video streams within a media channel.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
      <tp:flag suffix="NAT_Traversal_STUN" value="4">
        <tp:docstring>
          The handle is capable of performing STUN to traverse NATs.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
      <tp:flag suffix="NAT_Traversal_GTalk_P2P" value="8">
        <tp:docstring>
          The handle is capable of establishing Google Talk peer-to-peer
          connections (as implemented in libjingle 0.3) to traverse NATs.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
    </tp:flags>

  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
