<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Channel_Interface_Media_Signalling" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2005, 2006 Collabora Limited </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2005, 2006 Nokia Corporation </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2006 INdT </tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface.MediaSignalling">
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel"/>
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Type.StreamedMedia"/>

    <tp:simple-type name="Media_Session_Type" type="s">
      <tp:docstring>The type of a media session. Currently, the only supported
        value is "rtp".</tp:docstring>
    </tp:simple-type>

    <tp:struct name="Media_Session_Handler_Info"
        array-name="Media_Session_Handler_Info_List">
      <tp:docstring>A struct representing a active session handler.</tp:docstring>
      <tp:member type="o" name="Session_Handler">
        <tp:docstring>The object path of the session handler, which is on the
          same bus name as the channel.</tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="s" tp:type="Media_Session_Type" name="Media_Session_Type">
        <tp:docstring>The media session's type</tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
    </tp:struct>

    <method name="GetSessionHandlers"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Get_Session_Handlers">
      <arg direction="out" type="a(os)" tp:type="Media_Session_Handler_Info[]"/>
      <tp:docstring>
        Returns all currently active session handlers on this channel
        as a list of (session_handler_path, type).
      </tp:docstring>
    </method>

    <signal name="NewSessionHandler" tp:name-for-bindings="New_Session_Handler">
      <arg name="Session_Handler" type="o">
        <tp:docstring>
          Object path of the new MediaSessionHandler object
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="Session_Type" tp:type="Media_Session_Type" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          String indicating type of session, eg &quot;rtp&quot;
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Signal that a session handler object has been created. The client
        should create a session object and create streams for the streams
        within.
      </tp:docstring>
    </signal>
    <tp:property name="nat-traversal" type="s">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>A string indicating the NAT traversal techniques employed by the
      streams within this channel. Can be protocol-specific values, but the
      following values should be used if appropriate:</p>

      <dl>
        <dt>none</dt>
        <dd>No attempt should be made at NAT traversal.</dd>

        <dt>stun</dt>
        <dd>If appropriate, a STUN request should be made to the given server
        to open a UDP port mapping and determine the external IP.</dd>

        <dt>gtalk-p2p</dt>
        <dd>Google Talk peer-to-peer connectivity establishment should be used,
        as implemented in libjingle 0.3.</dd>
      </dl>
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>
    <tp:property name="stun-server" type="s">
      <tp:docstring>
      The IP address or hostname of the STUN server to use for NAT traversal.
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>
    <tp:property name="stun-port" type="q">
      <tp:docstring>
      The UDP port number to use on the provided STUN server.
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>
    <tp:property name="gtalk-p2p-relay-token" type="s">
      <tp:docstring>
      The authentication token for use with the Google Talk peer-to-peer relay
      server.
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:property>

    <tp:docstring>
      An interface for signalling a channel containing synchronised media
    sessions which can contain an arbitrary number of streams. The negotiation
    interface is based closely around the API of the Farsight library
    (http://farsight.sourceforge.net/). This in turn is based upon the IETF
    MMusic ICE drafts where connections are established by signalling potential
    connection candidates to the peer until a usable connection is found, and
    codecs are negotiated with an SDP-style offer and answer. However, the
    principles should be applicable to other media streaming methods and the
    API re-used without difficulty.
    </tp:docstring>
  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
