<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Channel_Interface_Messages"
  xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright>Copyright (C) 2008 Collabora Ltd.</tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright>Copyright (C) 2008 Nokia Corporation</tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301,
USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface
    name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface.Messages.DRAFT"
    tp:causes-havoc="experimental">
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Type.Text"/>
    <tp:added version="0.17.5">(draft version, not API-stable)</tp:added>

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>This interface extends the Text interface to support more general
        messages, including:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>messages with attachments (like MIME multipart/mixed)</li>
        <li>groups of alternatives (like MIME multipart/alternative)</li>
        <li>delivery reports</li>
        <li>any extra types of message we need in future</li>
      </ul>

      <p>It also provides a hook for improved sent
        message status notification, to be used by the DeliveryReporting
        interface.</p>

      <p>Although this specification supports formatted (rich-text)
        messages with unformatted alternatives, implementations SHOULD NOT
        attempt to send formatted messages until the Telepathy specification
        has also been extended to cover capability discovery for message
        formatting.</p>

      <tp:rationale>
        We intend to expose all rich-text messages as XHTML-IM, but on some
        protocols, formatting is an extremely limited subset of that format
        (e.g. there are protocols where foreground/background colours, font
        and size can be set, but only for entire messages).
        Until we can tell UIs what controls to offer to the user, it's
        unfriendly to offer the user controls that may have no effect.
      </tp:rationale>

      <p>If this interface is present, clients that support it SHOULD
        listen for the MessageSent and MessageReceived signals, and
        ignore the Sent and Received signal on the Text interface
        (which are guaranteed to duplicate signals from this interface).</p>
    </tp:docstring>

    <property name="SupportedContentTypes" type="as" access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        A list of MIME types supported by this channel, with more preferred
        MIME types appearing earlier in the list. The list MAY include "*/*"
        to indicate that attachments with arbitrary MIME types can be sent.
        If the list is empty, this indicates that messages may only include
        a single "text/plain" part.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="MessagePartSupportFlags" type="u"
      tp:type="Message_Part_Support_Flags"
      access="read">
      <tp:docstring>
        Flags indicating the level of support for message parts on this
        channel.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <tp:flags name="Message_Part_Support_Flags"
      value-prefix="Message_Part_Support_Flag">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Flags indicating the level of support for message parts on this
          channel. They are designed such that setting more flags always
          implies that the channel has more capabilities.</p>

        <p>It is assumed that messages containing a textual message body
          (only), like the messages the Text interface was designed for, are
          always supported.</p>

        <p>There is no flag indicating support for alternatives. This is
          because the SendMessage implementation can always accept messages
          containing alternatives, even if the underlying protocol does not,
          by deleting all alternatives except the first (most preferred)
          that is supported.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          Each of the flags 1, 2, 4 implies the previous flag, so we could
          have used a simple enumeration here; however, we've defined
          the message-part support indicator as a flag set for future
          expansion.
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>

      <tp:flag suffix="Data_Only" value="1">
        <tp:docstring>
          SendMessage will accept messages containing a single part of any
          type listed in the SupportedContentTypes property, with no
          accompanying text.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
      <tp:flag suffix="One_Attachment" value="2">
        <tp:docstring>
          SendMessage will accept messages containing a textual message body,
          plus a single attachment of any type listed in the
          SupportedContentTypes property. It does not make sense for this
          flag to be set if Message_Part_Support_Flag_Data_Only is not also set
          (because the connection manager can trivially provide an empty text
          part if necessary).
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
      <tp:flag suffix="Multiple_Attachments" value="4">
        <tp:docstring>
          SendMessage will accept messages containing a textual message body,
          plus an arbitrary number of attachments of any type listed in the
          SupportedContentTypes property. It does not make sense for this
          flag to be set if Message_Part_Support_Flag_One_Attachment is not
          also set.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
    </tp:flags>

    <tp:mapping name="Message_Part" array-name="Message_Part_List">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Part of a message's content. In practice, this mapping never
          appears in isolation - messages are represented by a list of
          <tp:type>Message_Part</tp:type> mappings.</p>

        <p>An example of how a message might
          look, in a Python-like syntax:</p>

          <pre>
[
  {
    'message-sender': 42,
    'message-sent': 1210067943,
    'message-received': 1210067947,
    'message-type': 0,
    'pending-message-id': 437,
  },
  { 'alternative': 'main',
    'type': 'text/html',
    'content': 'Here is a photo of my cat:&lt;br /&gt;' +
               '&lt;img src="cid:catphoto" alt="lol!" /&gt;' +
               '&lt;br /&gt;Isn't it cute?',
  },
  { 'alternative': 'main',
    'type': 'text/plain',
    'content': 'Here is a photo of my cat:\n[IMG: lol!]\nIsn't it cute?',
  },
  { 'identifier': 'catphoto',
    'type': 'image/jpeg',
    'size': 101000,
    'needs-retrieval': True,
  },
]
          </pre>

        <div>
          <p>The first part of the message contains "headers" which refer
            to the entire message.</p>

          <p>It is an error for a connection manager to put keys referring
            to the message as a whole in the second or subsequent
            Message_Part, but clients MUST recover from this error by ignoring
            these keys in the second and subsequent parts.</p>

          <p>Well-known keys for the message as a whole, and the corresponding
            value types, include:</p>

          <dl>
            <!-- FIXME: if needed we could add:
            <dt>message-identifier (s)</dt>
            <dd>An opaque, globally-unique identifier for the entire message.
              This MAY be treated as if it were a MIME Message-ID, e.g. for
              the mid: and cid: URI schemes. If omitted, there is no suitable
              identifier.</dd>
            -->

            <dt>message-sent (u - <tp:type>Unix_Timestamp</tp:type>)</dt>
            <dd>The time the message was sent (if unavailable, the time
              it arrived at a central server MAY be used). Omitted if no
              reasonable approximation is available</dd>

            <dt>message-received (u - <tp:type>Unix_Timestamp</tp:type>)</dt>
            <dd>The time the message was received locally. SHOULD always
              be present.</dd>

            <dt>message-sender (u - <tp:type>Contact_Handle</tp:type>)</dt>
            <dd>The contact who sent the message. If 0 or omitted, the contact
              who sent the message could not be determined.</dd>

            <dt>message-type (u - <tp:type>Channel_Text_Message_Type</tp:type>)
            </dt>
            <dd>The type of message; if omitted,
              Channel_Text_Message_Type_Normal MUST be assumed. SHOULD
              be omitted for normal chat messages.</dd>

            <dt>pending-message-id (u - <tp:type>Message_ID</tp:type>)</dt>
            <dd>The incoming message ID. This MUST NOT be present on outgoing
              messages. Clients SHOULD NOT store this key - it is only valid
              for as long as the message remains unacknowledged.</dd>

            <dt>interface (s - <tp:type>DBus_Interface</tp:type>)</dt>
            <dd>This message is specific to the given interface, which is
              neither Text nor Messages. It SHOULD be ignored if that
              interface is not supported. (Note that an 'interface' key
              can also appear on the second and subsequent parts, where
              it indicates that that part (only) should be ignored if
              unsupported.)</dd>
          </dl>
        </div>

        <div>
          <p>The second and subsequent parts contain the message's
            content, including plain text, formatted text and/or attached
            files.</p>

          <p>In any group of parts with the same non-empty value for the
            "alternative" key (which represent alternative versions of the
            same content), more faithful versions of the intended message MUST
            come before less faithful versions (note that this order is the
            opposite of MIME "multipart/alternative" parts). Clients SHOULD
            display the first alternative that they understand.</p>

          <tp:rationale>
            Specifying the preference order means that if the underlying
            protocol doesn't support alternatives, the CM can safely delete
            everything apart from the first supported alternative when sending
            messages.
          </tp:rationale>

          <p>Clients SHOULD present all parts that are not redundant
            alternatives in the order they appear in this array, possibly
            excluding parts that are referenced by another displayed part.
            It is implementation-specific how the parts are presented to the
            user.</p>

          <tp:rationale>
            <p>This allows CMs to assume that all parts are actually shown to
              the user, even if they are not explicitly referenced - we do
              not yet recommend formatted text, and there is no way for
              plain text to reference an attachment since it has no concept of
              markup or references. This also forces clients to do something
              sensible with messages that consist entirely of "attachments",
              with no "body" at all.</p>

            <p>For instance, when displaying the above example, a client that
              understands the HTML part should display the JPEG image once,
              between the two lines "Here is a photo of my cat:" and
              "Isn't it cute?"; it may additionally present the image in some
              way for a second time, after "Isn't it cute?", or may choose
              not to.</p>

            <p>A client that does not understand HTML, displaying the same
              message, should display the plain-text part, followed by the JPEG
              image.</p>
          </tp:rationale>

          <p>Well-known keys for the second and subsequent parts, and the
            corresponding value types, include:</p>

          <dl>
            <dt>identifier (s)</dt>
            <dd>An opaque identifier for this part.
              Parts of a message MAY reference other parts by treating
              this identifier as if it were a MIME Content-ID and using
              the cid: URI scheme.</dd>

            <dt>alternative (s)</dt>
            <dd>
              <p>If present, this part of the message is an alternative for
                all other parts with the same value for "alternative".
                Clients SHOULD only display one of them (this is expected to
                be used for XHTML messages in a future version of this
                specification).</p>

              <p>If omitted, this part is not an alternative for any other
                part.</p>

              <p>Parts of a message MAY reference the group of alternatives
                as a whole (i.e. a reference to whichever of them is chosen)
                by treating this identifier as if it were the MIME Content-ID
                of a multipart/alternative part, and using the cid: URI
                scheme.</p>
            </dd>

            <dt>type (s)</dt>
            <dd>
              <p>The MIME type of this part. See the documentation
                for ReceivedMessage for notes on the special status of
                "text/plain" parts.</p>

              <p>Connection managers MUST NOT signal parts without a 'type'
                key; if a protocol provides no way to determine the MIME type,
                the connection manager is responsible for guessing it, but
                MAY fall back to "text/plain" for text and
                "application/octet-stream" for non-text.</p>

              <p>Clients MUST ignore parts without a 'type' key, which are
                reserved for future expansion.</p>
            </dd>

            <dt>lang (s)</dt>
            <dd>The natural language of this part, identified by a
              RFC 3066 language tag.

              <tp:rationale>
                XMPP allows alternative-selection by language as well as
                by content-type.
              </tp:rationale>
            </dd>

            <dt>size (u)</dt>
            <dd>The size in bytes (if needs-retrieval is true, this MAY be an
              estimated or approximate size). SHOULD be omitted if 'content'
              is provided.

              <tp:rationale>
                There's no point in providing the size if you're already
                providing all the content.
              </tp:rationale>
              </dd>

            <dt>needs-retrieval (b)</dt>
            <dd>If false or omitted, the connection
              manager already holds this part in memory. If present and true,
              this part will be retrieved on demand (like MIME's
              message/external-body), so clients should expect retrieval to
              take time; if this specification is later extended to provide a
              streaming version of GetPendingMessageContent, clients should
              use it for parts with this flag.</dd>

            <dt>truncated (b)</dt>
            <dd>The content available via the 'content' key or
              GetPendingMessageContent has been truncated by the server
              or connection manager (equivalent to
              Channel_Text_Message_Flag_Truncated in the Text interface).
            </dd>

            <dt>content (s or ay)</dt>
            <dd>The part's content, if it is available and
              sufficiently small to include here (implies that
              'needs-retrieval' is false or omitted). Otherwise, omitted.
              If the part is human-readable text or HTML, the value for this
              key MUST be a UTF-8 string (D-Bus signature 's').
              If the part is not text, the value MUST be a byte-array
              (D-Bus signature 'ay'). If the part is a text-based format
              that is not the main body of the message (e.g. an iCalendar
              or an attached XML document), the value SHOULD be a UTF-8 string,
              transcoding from another charset to UTF-8 if necessary, but
              MAY be a byte-array (of unspecified character set) if
              transcoding fails or the source charset is not known.</dd>

              <!-- FIXME: "sufficiently small to include" is not currently
              defined; we should add some API so clients can tell the
                CM how large a message it should emit in the signal.-->

            <dt>interface (s - <tp:type>DBus_Interface</tp:type>)</dt>
            <dd>This part is specific to the given interface, which is
              neither Text nor Messages. It SHOULD be ignored if that
              interface is not supported. (Note that an 'interface' key
              can also appear on the first part, where it indicates that the
              entire message should be ignored if unsupported.)</dd>
          </dl>

          <p>It is an error for a connection manager to put these keys
            in the first <tp:type>Message_Part</tp:type>, but clients MUST be
            able to recover from this error by ignoring these keys in the
            first part.</p>

        </div>
      </tp:docstring>

      <tp:member name="Key" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          A key, which SHOULD be one of the well-known keys specified, if
          possible.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>

      <tp:member name="Value" type="v">
        <tp:docstring>
          The value corresponding to the given key, which must be of one of
          the types indicated.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
    </tp:mapping>


    <tp:simple-type type="s" name="Sent_Message_Token">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>An opaque token used to identify sent messages. As a special case,
          the empty string indicates that there is no particular
          identification for a message.</p>

        <p>CM implementations SHOULD use an identifier expected to be unique,
          such as a UUID, if possible.</p>

        <p>Some protocols can only track a limited number of sent messages
          in a small message-ID space. As a result, clients MUST NOT assume
          that message tokens will not be re-used, and SHOULD use some
          reasonable heuristic to assign delivery reports to messages, such
          as matching on message content or timestamp (if available), or
          assuming that the delivery report refers to the most recent message
          with that ID.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>This is a hook for the DeliveryReporting interface,
            to avoid having to introduce a
            SendMultiPartMessageAndReturnToken method in that interface.</p>
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:simple-type>

    <method name="SendMessage">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Submit a message to the server for sending.
          If this method returns successfully, the message has been submitted
          to the server and the MessageSent signal is emitted. A corresponding
          Sent signal on the Text interface MUST also be emitted.</p>

        <p>If this method fails, message submission to the server has failed
          and no signal on this interface (or the Text interface) is
          emitted.</p>
      </tp:docstring>

      <arg direction="in" type="aa{sv}" tp:type="Message_Part[]"
        name="Message">
        <tp:docstring>
          The message content, including any attachments or alternatives
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="Flags" type="u"
        tp:type="Message_Sending_Flags">
        <tp:docstring>
          Flags affecting how the message is sent.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg direction="out" type="s" tp:type="Sent_Message_Token">
        <tp:docstring>
          An opaque token used to match any incoming delivery or failure
          reports against this message, or an empty string if the message
          is not readily identifiable.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidArgument">
          <tp:docstring>
            The requested message is malformed and cannot be sent.
          </tp:docstring>
        </tp:error>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.PermissionDenied"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <tp:flags name="Message_Sending_Flags" value-prefix="Message_Sending_Flag">
      <tp:docstring>
        Flags altering the way a message is sent. The "most usual" action
        should always be to have these flags unset.
      </tp:docstring>

      <tp:flag suffix="Report_Delivery" value="1">
        <tp:docstring>
          Provide a delivery report via the DeliveryReporting interface, if
          possible, even if this is not the default for this protocol.
          Ignored if delivery reports are not possible on this protocol.

          <tp:rationale>
            In some protocols, like XMPP, it is not conventional to request
            or send delivery notifications.
          </tp:rationale>
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
    </tp:flags>

    <signal name="MessageSent">
      <tp:docstring>
        Signals that a message has been submitted for sending. This
        MUST be emitted exactly once per emission of the Sent signal on the
        Text interface.

        <tp:rationale>
          This signal allows a process that is not the caller of
          SendMessage to log sent messages. The double signal-emission
          means that clients can safely follow the following rule:
          if the channel has the Messages interface, listen for
          Messages.MessageSent only; otherwise, listen for Text.Sent only.
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>

      <arg type="aa{sv}" tp:type="Message_Part[]" name="Content">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          The message content (see <tp:type>Message_Part</tp:type> for full
          details). If the message that was passed to SendMessage has a
          formatted text part that the connection manager recognises, but no
          text/plain alternative, the CM MUST use the formatted text part to
          generate a text/plain alternative which is also included in this
          signal argument.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg name="Message_Token" type="s" tp:type="Sent_Message_Token">
        <tp:docstring>
          An opaque token used to match any incoming delivery or failure
          reports against this message, or an empty string if the message
          is not readily identifiable.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
    </signal>

    <property name="PendingMessages" type="aaa{sv}" access="read"
      tp:type="Message_Part[][]">
      <tp:docstring>
        A list of incoming messages that have neither been acknowledged nor
        rejected. This list is a superset of the one returned by
        ListPendingMessages on the Text interface; its items can be removed
        using AcknowledgePendingMessages on that interface.
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <signal name="PendingMessagesRemoved">
      <tp:docstring>
        The messages with the given IDs have been removed from the
        PendingMessages list. Clients SHOULD NOT attempt to acknowledge
        those messages.

        <tp:rationale>
          This completes change notification for the PendingMessages property
          (previously, there was change notification when pending messages
          were added, but not when they were removed).
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>

      <arg name="Message_IDs" type="au" tp:type="Message_ID[]">
        <tp:docstring>
          The messages that have been removed from the pending message list.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
    </signal>

    <method name="GetPendingMessageContent">
      <tp:docstring>
        Retrieve the content of one or more parts of a pending message.
        Note that this function may take a considerable amount of time
        to return if the part's 'needs-retrieval' flag is true; consider
        extending the default D-Bus method call timeout. Additional API is
        likely to be added in future, to stream large message parts.
      </tp:docstring>

      <arg name="Message_ID" type="u" tp:type="Message_ID" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          The ID of a pending message
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg name="Parts" type="au" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          The desired entries in the array of message parts, identified by
          their position. The "headers" part (which is not a valid argument
          to this method) is considered to be part 0, so the valid part
          numbers start at 1 (for the second Message_Part).
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg name="Content" type="a{uv}" direction="out">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          <p>The content of the requested parts. The keys in this mapping
            are positions in the array of message parts; the values are
            either of type 's' or 'ay' (UTF-8 text string, or byte array),
            following the same rules as for the value of the 'content' key in
            the <tp:type>Message_Part</tp:type> mappings.</p>

          <p>If the one of the requested part numbers was greater than zero
            but referred to a part that had no content (i.e. it had no 'type'
            key or no 'content' key), it is simply omitted from this mapping;
            this is not considered to be an error condition.</p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidArgument">
          <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
            Either there is no pending message with the given message ID,
            or one of the part numbers given was 0 or too large.
          </tp:docstring>
        </tp:error>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.PermissionDenied"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <signal name="MessageReceived">
      <tp:docstring>
        Signals that a message has been received and added to the pending
        messages queue. This MUST be emitted exactly once per emission of the
        Received signal on the Text interface.

        <tp:rationale>
          The double signal-emission means that clients can safely follow
          the following rule: if the channel has the Messages interface,
          listen for Messages.MessageReceived only; otherwise, listen for
          Text.Received only.
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>

      <arg type="aa{sv}" tp:type="Message_Part[]" name="Message">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          The message content, including any attachments or alternatives
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
    </signal>

  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
