<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Channel_Interface_Message_Archive"
  xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright>Copyright © 2016 Alexandr Akulich</tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301,
USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface
    name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface.MessageArchive">
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Type.Text"/>
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface.Messages"/>
    <tp:added version="0.28.0"/>

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>This interface extends the <tp:dbus-ref
          namespace='org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Type'>Text</tp:dbus-ref>
        interface to support logs retrieval</p>

      <p>If this interface is present, clients SHOULD listen for the <tp:dbus-ref
          namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface.Messages">MessageReceived</tp:dbus-ref>
          signal for requested scrollback messages.
      </p>
    </tp:docstring>

    <tp:simple-type name="Message_Filter_Key" type="s">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <dl>
          <dt>limit (u)</dt>
          <dd>Maximum number of messages to be returned. Must be supported by all CMs and must be presented in all request. If 0, the number of messages is unlimited.</dd>

          <dt>offset (u)</dt>
          <dd>Number of messages to be skipped. Usually goes well with the 'message-token' key.</dd>
            
          <dt>message-token (s - <tp:type>Protocol_Message_Token</tp:type>)</dt>
          <dd>If specified, the connection manager MUST only return messages starting with the referenced one. This key is not compatible with the 'start-timestamp' key.</dd>

          <dt>start-timestamp (x - <tp:type>Unix_Timestamp64</tp:type>)</dt>
          <dd>A value to filter out messages before a certain date/time. If specified,
              the connection manager MUST only return messages whose timestamp is equal to or later
              than the given timestamp.
          </dd>

          <dt>end-timestamp (x - <tp:type>Unix_Timestamp64</tp:type>)</dt>
          <dd>A value to filter out messages after a certain date/time. If specified,
              the connection manager MUST only return messages whose timestamp is equal to or earlier
              than the given timestamp.
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </tp:docstring>
    </tp:simple-type>

    <tp:mapping name="Message_Filter_Map">
      <tp:docstring>A map from filter keys to values.</tp:docstring>
      <tp:member name="Key" type="s" tp:type="Message_Filter_Key">
        <tp:docstring>
          The filter key to match against.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>

      <tp:member name="Value" type="v">
        <tp:docstring>
          The value of the corresponding filter key.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
    </tp:mapping>
    
    <method name="GetMessages" tp:name-for-bindings="Get_Messages">
      <arg direction="in" name="Filter"
        type="a{sv}" tp:type="Message_Filter_Map">
        <tp:docstring>
          A dictionary mapping filter key names to the desired values
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        <h4>Example calls</h4>
            <p>A request for 20 messages after a certain one might be represented as:</p>
          <pre>
{
  'limit': 20,
  'offset': 1, # Skip the known message
  'message-token': '9de9546a-3400-4419-a505-3ea270cb834c',
}</pre>
            <p>A request for a single message by its token:</p>
          <pre>
{
  'limit': 1,
  'offset': 0, # Can be omitted
  'message-token': '9de9546a-3400-4419-a505-3ea270cb834c',
}</pre>
            <p>A request for all messages in a certain timespan:</p>
          <pre>
{
  'limit': 0,
  'start-timestamp': 1210123456,
  'end-timestamp': 1210234567,
}</pre>
      </tp:docstring>
    </method>
    <property name="AvailableFilterKeys" type="as" access="read"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Available_Filter_Keys" tp:immutable='yes'>
        <tp:docstring>
          <p>List of available filter keys, sorted by preference (more suitable keys listed first).</p>
          <tp:rationale>
            <p>Various protocols have different history retrieval API. Order of the keys let the CM
               to inform a client about possible overhead of various API calls (especially in case if the CM supports one API is ontop of the other).</p>
            <p>For instance, XMPP with XEP-0313 natively supports filtering by time received, but emulation
               of "offset from a message-token" API would take an uncertain amount of traffic and would be tricky.</p>
            <p>On the other side, Telegram offers the "skip N messages after the message X and return M messages that" API and it would require to get
               all messages in order to filter them by timestamp.</p>
          </tp:rationale>
        </tp:docstring>
    </property>
  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
