<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Channel_Type_Contact_List" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2005, 2006 Collabora Limited </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2005, 2006 Nokia Corporation </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2006 INdT </tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Type.ContactList">
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel"/>
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface.Group"/>

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>A channel type for representing a list of people on the server which is
    not used for communication. This is intended for use with the interface
    Channel.Interface.Group for managing buddy lists and privacy lists
    on the server. This channel type has no methods because all of the
    functionality it represents is available via the group interface.</p>

    <p>There are currently two types of contact list:
    HANDLE_TYPE_LIST is a &quot;magic&quot; server-defined list, and
    HANDLE_TYPE_GROUP is a user-defined contact group.</p>

    <p>For server-defined lists like the subscribe list, singleton instances
    of this channel type should be created by the connection manager at
    connection time if the list exists on the server, or may be requested
    by using the appropriate handle.  These handles can be obtained using
    RequestHandles with a handle type of HANDLE_TYPE_LIST and
    one of the following identifiers:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>subscribe - the group of contacts for whom you wish to receive presence</li>
      <li>publish - the group of contacts who may receive your presence</li>
      <li>hide - a group of contacts who are on the publish list but are temporarily disallowed from receiving your presence</li>
      <li>allow - a group of contacts who may send you messages</li>
      <li>deny - a group of contacts who may not send you messages</li>
    </ul>

    <p>These contact list channels may not be closed.</p>

    <p>For user-defined contact groups, instances of this channel type should
    be created by the connection manager at connection time for each group
    that exists on the server. New, empty groups can be created by calling
    RequestHandles with a handle type of
    HANDLE_TYPE_GROUP and with the name set to the
    human-readable UTF-8 name of the group.</p>

    <p>User-defined groups may be deleted by closing the channel, but only if
    the group is already empty. Closing a channel to a non-empty group is
    not allowed; its members must be set to the empty set first.</p>

    <p>On some protocols (e.g. XMPP) empty groups are not represented on the
    server, so disconnecting from the server and reconnecting might cause
    empty groups to vanish.</p>
    </tp:docstring>

  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
