<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Channel_Interface_Media_Signalling_Future"
  xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2009 Collabora Limited </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2009 Nokia Corporation </tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
      modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
      License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
      version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

    <p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
      but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
      MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
      Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

    <p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
      License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
      Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301,
      USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface.MediaSignalling.FUTURE">
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel"/>
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Type.StreamedMedia"/>
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Type.MediaSignalling"/>

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>This interface contains functionality which we intend to incorporate
        into the <tp:dbus-ref
          namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Channel.Interface.MediaSignalling</tp:dbus-ref>
        interface in future. It should be considered to be conceptually part
        of the core MediaSignalling interface, but without API or ABI
        guarantees.</p>

      <tp:rationale>
        <p>The rationale is the same as for <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Channel.FUTURE</tp:dbus-ref>.</p>
      </tp:rationale>
    </tp:docstring>

    <property name="ICETransportAvailable"
      tp:name-for-bindings="ICE_Transport_Available"
      type="b" access="read">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>True if this channel supports the use of the ICE-UDP transport
          (<a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0176.html">XEP-0176</a>,
          <a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-mmusic-ice">ICE RFC
            draft)</a>. Various other transports have boolean properties
          that work in the same way as this one, so this description covers
          all such transports.</p>

        <p>This property is immutable (cannot change), and therefore SHOULD
          appear wherever immutable properties are reported, e.g. <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.Requests">NewChannels</tp:dbus-ref>
          signals.</p>

        <p>Connection managers capable of signalling streamed media calls to
          contacts SHOULD include the properties representing all supported
          transports in the allowed properties list of the channel class
          in <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.Requests">RequestableChannelClasses</tp:dbus-ref>
          that advertises support for streamed media channels.</p>

        <p>Similarly, connection managers that support the <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface">ContactCapabilities.DRAFT</tp:dbus-ref>
          interface SHOULD include all supported transports in the allowed
          properties list of the channel class that advertises a contact's
          ability to receive streamed media calls.</p>

        <p>Clients that are able to receive calls with particular NAT
          traversal mechanisms MAY include the following filters if
          calling <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.ContactCapabilities.DRAFT">SetSelfCapabilities</tp:dbus-ref>
          (clients of a <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">ChannelDispatcher.DRAFT</tp:dbus-ref>
          SHOULD instead arrange for the ChannelDispatcher to do this,
          by including the filters in their <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Client.Handler.DRAFT">HandlerChannelFilter</tp:dbus-ref>
          properties):</p>

        <ul>
          <li>{ ChannelType = StreamedMedia, ICETransportAvailable = true }
            if the ICE transport is supported</li>
          <li>{ ChannelType = StreamedMedia, RawUDPTransportAvailable = true }
            if the raw UDP transport is supported</li>
          <li>... and so on, one filter per available transport.</li>
        </ul>

        <p>Connection managers MAY use this information to adjust the
          transports for which they advertise support to other contacts.
          If a client has indicated support for any particular transports,
          the connection manager SHOULD advertise support for
          each transport that is supported by any client, and also
          supported by the CM itself.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>This minimizes the possibility that a call will be started that
            cannot in fact succeed, because the intersection of the contacts'
            available transports is empty.</p>
        </tp:rationale>

        <p>If no client has mentioned any of the transports known to the
          connection manager in a call to SetSelfCapabilities, the connection
          manager SHOULD advertise support for every transport that it can
          signal.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>This simplifies implementation on integrated platforms like Maemo,
            where it can be assumed that client libraries will support all the
            "standard" transports known to any connection manager, and
            lowers the "barrier to entry" for new Telepathy clients.</p>
        </tp:rationale>

        <p>Clients making outgoing calls for which the same client that made
          the request will handle the streaming MAY indicate their ability or
          inability to handle particular transports by including
          <code>ICETransportAvailable = true</code>,
          <code>RawUDPTransportAvailable = false</code>, etc.
          in the request properties parameter of their call to <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.Requests">EnsureChannel</tp:dbus-ref>
          or similar functions. When they do so, the connection manager
          SHOULD attempt to use a transport that the client has indicated
          it is able to handle; if this is not possible, the connection
          manager SHOULD raise an error instead of creating a channel.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>This enables such clients to restrict the CM to the subset of
            transports supported by that particular client.</p>
        </tp:rationale>

        <p>Clients making outgoing calls for which they will not themselves
          handle the streaming (e.g. an address book starting a call which
          will be streamed by a separate call UI) SHOULD NOT include those
          properties in the request.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>In general, such a client can't know the capabilities of the
            streaming implementation, or even which streaming implementation
            will be used.</p>
        </tp:rationale>

        <p>In the absence of any indication of supported transports from the
          client, the connection manager SHOULD assume that the transports
          indicated by calling SetSelfCapabilities are available. If
          no transports were indicated as supported by calling
          SetSelfCapabilities either, it SHOULD assume that any transport
          that it can signal will be acceptable.</p>

        <p>If this property, or any of the similar transport availability
          properties, is passed to EnsureChannel (as opposed to CreateChannel),
          the connection manager SHOULD ignore these properties when checking
          whether it can return an existing channel as suitable; these
          properties only become significant when the connection manager has
          decided to create a new channel.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="RawUDPTransportAvailable"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Raw_UDP_Transport_Available"
      type="b" access="read">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The same as <tp:member-ref>ICETransportAvailable</tp:member-ref>,
          but for raw UDP streaming as described by <a
            href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0177.html">XEP-0177</a>.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="GoogleP2PTransportAvailable"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Google_P2P_Transport_Available"
      type="b" access="read">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The same as <tp:member-ref>ICETransportAvailable</tp:member-ref>,
          but for the variant of ICE used by the Google Talk peer-to-peer
          connectivity establishment mechanism (as implemented in libjingle
          0.3).</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="MSNTransportAvailable"
      tp:name-for-bindings="MSN_Transport_Available"
      type="b" access="read">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The same as <tp:member-ref>ICETransportAvailable</tp:member-ref>,
          but for the variant of ICE used by MSN.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

  </interface>
</node>
