<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Channel_Interface_Captcha_Authentication"
      xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright> Copyright © 2010-2012 Collabora Limited </tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel.Interface.CaptchaAuthentication1">
    <tp:added version="0.25.2">(version 1)</tp:added>
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel"/>
    <annotation name="org.freedesktop.DBus.Property.EmitsChangedSignal"
      value="true"/>
    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>A channel interface for captcha authentication.
        When this interface appears on a <tp:dbus-ref
          namespace="ofdT.Channel.Type">ServerAuthentication</tp:dbus-ref>
        channel, it represents authentication with the server. In future,
        it could also be used to authenticate with secondary services,
        or even to authenticate end-to-end connections with contacts. As a result,
        this interface does not REQUIRE <tp:dbus-ref namespace="ofdT.Channel.Type"
        >ServerAuthentication</tp:dbus-ref> to allow for a potential future
        Channel.Type.PeerAuthentication interface.</p>

      <p>In any protocol that requires a captcha, the connection manager can
        use this channel to let a user interface carry out a simple captcha
        handshake with it, as a way to test the user is human
        interactively.</p>

      <p>For channels managed by a
        <tp:dbus-ref namespace="ofdT">ChannelDispatcher</tp:dbus-ref>,
        only the channel's <tp:dbus-ref
          namespace="ofdT.Client">Handler</tp:dbus-ref> may call the
        methods on this interface. Other clients MAY observe the
        authentication process by watching its signals and properties.</p>

      <p>The most commonly used form of captcha challenge is OCR (recognition
        of distorted letters or words in an image), but for accessibility
        reasons, this interface also allows various other types of challenge,
        such as plain-text questions or recognition of words in audio. Its
        structure is modelled on XMPP's
        <a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0158.html">XEP-0158</a>,
        but can be used with other protocols by mapping their semantics
        into those used in XMPP.</p>

      <tp:rationale>
        <p>It is important to support multiple types of captcha
          challenge to avoid discriminating against certain users; for
          instance, blind or partially-sighted users cannot be expected
          to answer an OCR challenge.</p>

        <p>XEP-0158 supports a superset of all other known protocols' captcha
          interfaces, and is sufficiently elaborate that we expect it will
          continue to do so.</p>

        <p>There can only be one Handler, which is a good fit for the
          question/answer model implied by captchas.</p>
      </tp:rationale>
    </tp:docstring>

    <tp:struct name="Captcha_Info" array-name="Captcha_Info_List">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>A struct containing information regarding a single captcha
          mechanism.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:member type="u" name="ID">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          <p>The ID with which to reference this captcha method
            when retrieving its data and answering it.
            They are unique within this channel instance only.</p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="s" name="Type">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          <p>The type of challenge
            <a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0158.html#challenge">
            as defined by XEP-0158</a>. For instance, the commonly-used
            "type the letters/words you see in this image" challenge is
            represented by <code>ocr</code></p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="s" name="Label">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          <p>A human-readable label for the challenge, as defined in
            XEP-0158.</p>

          <p>If the server does not supply a label for a challenge of type
            other than <code>qa</code>, connection managers SHOULD set Label
            to an empty string instead of generating their own text.
            If the Label is an empty string, the Handler SHOULD replace
            it with a generic label in the user's locale, such as
            the strings suggested in XEP-0158 (for instance,
            <code>Enter the text you see</code> for <code>ocr</code>
            challenges). The Handler MAY use those generic labels
            in any case, as per
            <a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0158.html#i18n">the
              Internationalization Considerations section of XEP-0158</a>.</p>

          <tp:rationale>
            <p>Connection managers are not usually localized, so text
              generated by the connection manager would be in English,
              regardless of the user's locale. The Handler is better-placed
              to generate a generic Label in the user's locale.</p>
          </tp:rationale>

          <p>For challenges of type <code>qa</code>, the Label is a plain-text
            question for the user to answer. The connection manager
            SHOULD NOT provide an empty Label; if it does, the Handler
            SHOULD treat that challenge as impossible, and SHOULD NOT
            attempt to display it.</p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="u" name="Flags" tp:type="Captcha_Flags">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          <p>One flag defined: Required. Most captchas will have no flags.</p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="as" name="Available_MIME_Types">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          <p>A list of MIME types the server is offering to provide
            for this captcha method.</p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
    </tp:struct>

    <tp:mapping name="Captcha_Answers">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        A mapping of captcha IDs to answer strings.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:member type="u" name="ID">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          The ID of the captcha to which the associated
          answer string is answering.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="s" name="Answer">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          The answer string to answer the captcha referenced
          by the associated ID.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
    </tp:mapping>

    <property name="CanRetryCaptcha"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Can_Retry_Captcha"
      type="b" access="read" tp:immutable="yes">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>If true, <tp:member-ref>GetCaptchas</tp:member-ref>
          can be expected to return new captcha information when
          in the Local_Pending state. If false,
          <tp:member-ref>GetCaptchas</tp:member-ref> will return
          NotAvailable on subsequent calls.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>Refreshing the captcha isn't required to work, although
            some protocols and implementations allow it. This is usually
            done in case a given captcha is unintelligible.</p>
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property type="u" tp:type="Captcha_Status" access="read"
      name="CaptchaStatus" tp:name-for-bindings="Captcha_Status">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The current status of this channel.</p>

        <p>Because only the Handler should call methods on this interface,
          the Handler MAY reduce round-trips by not fetching the initial
          value of this property, and instead assume that is initially
          Local_Pending.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>This assumption normally avoids the need to call GetAll(),
            since the values of <tp:member-ref>CaptchaError</tp:member-ref>
            and <tp:member-ref>CaptchaErrorDetails</tp:member-ref>
            are also implied by this assumption, and the only other
            property is <tp:member-ref>CanRetryCaptcha</tp:member-ref>,
            which is immutable.</p>
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property type="s" tp:type="DBus_Error_Name" access="read"
      name="CaptchaError" tp:name-for-bindings="Captcha_Error">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The reason for the <tp:member-ref>CaptchaStatus</tp:member-ref>, or
          an empty string if the state is neither Try_Again nor Failed.</p>

        <p>Typical values: "", Cancelled, AuthenticationFailed,
          CaptchaNotSupported</p>

        <p>In particular, an ordinary authentication failure (as would
          be produced for an incorrect answer) SHOULD be represented by
          <tp:error-ref>AuthenticationFailed</tp:error-ref>,
          cancellation by the user's request SHOULD be represented
          by <tp:error-ref>Cancelled</tp:error-ref>, cancellation due
          to the inability to display the captcha to the user or otherwise
          answer it SHOULD be represented by
          <tp:error-ref>CaptchaNotSupported</tp:error-ref>, and
          cancellation by a local process due to inconsistent or invalid
          challenges from the server SHOULD be represented by
          <tp:error-ref>ServiceConfused</tp:error-ref>.</p>

        <p>If this interface appears on a <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="ofdT.Channel.Type">ServerAuthentication</tp:dbus-ref>
          channel, and connection to the server fails with an authentication
          failure, this error code SHOULD be copied into the
          <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="ofdT">Connection.ConnectionError</tp:dbus-ref>
          signal.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="CaptchaErrorDetails"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Captcha_Error_Details"
      access="read" type="a{sv}" tp:type="String_Variant_Map">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>If <tp:member-ref>CaptchaError</tp:member-ref> is non-empty,
          any additional information about the last
          disconnection; otherwise, the empty map. The keys and values are
          the same as for the second argument of
          <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="ofdT">Connection.ConnectionError</tp:dbus-ref>.</p>

        <p>If this interface appears on a <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="ofdT.Channel.Type">ServerAuthentication</tp:dbus-ref>
          channel, and connection to the server fails with an authentication
          failure, these details SHOULD be copied into the
          <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="ofdT">Connection.ConnectionError</tp:dbus-ref>
          signal.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <method name="GetCaptchas" tp:name-for-bindings="Get_Captchas">
      <arg direction="out" name="Captcha_Info"
        type="a(ussuas)" tp:type="Captcha_Info[]">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          Information about each of the available captcha methods.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" name="Number_Required" type="u">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          The number of captcha methods required to be answered
          in order to successfully complete this captcha challenge
          (most frequently 1, but XMPP allows servers to demand that
          more than one captcha is answered).
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" name="Language" type="s" tp:type="Language_Tag">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          The language of each Label in Captcha_Info if available,
          for instance en_US, or "" if unknown.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Gets information regarding each of the captcha methods
          available and which and how many need to be successfully answered</p>

        <p>To call this method successfully, the state must be Local_Pending
          or Try_Again. If it is Local_Pending, it remains Local_Pending. If
          called more than once while in Local_Pending state, or if the state
          is Try_Again, this method fetches a new set of captcha challenges,
          if possible, and the state returns to Local_Pending.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>For instance, you could call GetCaptchas again from Local_Pending
            state if the user indicates that they can't understand the
            initially-offered captcha.</p>

          <p>This is a method, not a property, so that it can be used to
            fetch more than one set of captcha challenges, and so that
            change notification is not required. Only the Handler should
            call this method and calling GetAll would not reduce round-trips,
            so the usual reasons to prefer a property do not apply here.</p>
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>

      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable">
          <tp:docstring>
            Either the state is not Local_Pending or Try_Again, or it has
            already been called and
            <tp:member-ref>CanRetryCaptcha</tp:member-ref> is False.
          </tp:docstring>
        </tp:error>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <method name="GetCaptchaData" tp:name-for-bindings="Get_Captcha_Data">
      <arg direction="in" name="ID" type="u">
        <tp:docstring>
          The ID of the captcha of which to retrieve data.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="Mime_Type" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          MIME type picked by the Handler, chosen from the list of MIME
          types received in <tp:member-ref>GetCaptchas</tp:member-ref>.
          <tp:rationale>
            XEP-0158 allows the same captcha to be made available in
            multiple formats, for instance the same spoken question as
            audio/x-wav, application/ogg and audio/speex.
          </tp:rationale>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" name="Captcha_Data" type="ay">
        <tp:docstring>
          Captcha data as requested.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Fetch and return the captcha data. In protocols
          where captchas are downloaded out-of-band (for instance via HTTP),
          the connection manager is expected to do so.</p>
        <p>Returns an empty array if the type was "qa"</p>
        <tp:rationale>
          <p>If audio-based and image-based captchas are both available,
            we don't want to waste time downloading the audio until/unless
            the user asks to hear it. The extra D-Bus round-trips are not
            a problem, since they are expected to be quick compared with
            the time taken for the user to solve the captcha.</p>
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable">
          <tp:docstring>
            The state is not in Local_Pending or
            <tp:member-ref>GetCaptchas</tp:member-ref> had never been called.
          </tp:docstring>
        </tp:error>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <method name="AnswerCaptchas" tp:name-for-bindings="Answer_Captchas">
      <arg direction="in" name="Answers"
        type="a{us}" tp:type="Captcha_Answers">
        <tp:docstring>
          The mapping of captcha IDs to answer strings.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Answer as many captchas as desired and/or required.</p>
        <p>Callable in state Local_Pending only. State changes to
          Remote_Pending.</p>
      </tp:docstring>

      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable">
          <tp:docstring>
            The state is not in Local_Pending.
          </tp:docstring>
        </tp:error>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <method name="CancelCaptcha" tp:name-for-bindings="Cancel_Captcha">
      <arg direction="in" name="Reason"
        type="u" tp:type="Captcha_Cancel_Reason">
        <tp:docstring>
          Reason for cancelling. This MAY be used to choose an error
          response to the remote server, and SHOULD also be reflected
          in the <tp:member-ref>CaptchaError</tp:member-ref>.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="Debug_Message" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          A textual description of the reason for cancelling, supplied
          by the Handler. This message SHOULD NOT be sent to the remote
          server, but SHOULD be copied into the 'debug-message' field
          of the <tp:member-ref>CaptchaErrorDetails</tp:member-ref> and
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="ofdT.Connection">ConnectionError</tp:dbus-ref>.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Cancel. State changes to Failed with error NotAvailable or
          Cancelled if it isn't already Failed. All you can do now is
          to close the channel.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable">
          <tp:docstring>
            The current state is Failed.
          </tp:docstring>
        </tp:error>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <tp:flags name="Captcha_Flags" type="u">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Extra flags to include with Captcha information</p>
      </tp:docstring>

      <tp:flag suffix="Required" value="1">
        <tp:docstring>
          This captcha mechanism is required to be successfully
          answered in order to pass this captcha challenge.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
    </tp:flags>

    <tp:enum name="Captcha_Cancel_Reason" type="u">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>A reason why captcha authentication was aborted by the client.</p>
      </tp:docstring>

      <tp:enumvalue suffix="User_Cancelled" value="0">
        <tp:docstring>
          The user aborted the authentication. If this is used, the
          <tp:member-ref>CaptchaError</tp:member-ref> SHOULD be set to
          <tp:error-ref>Cancelled</tp:error-ref>
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Not_Supported" value="1">
        <tp:docstring>
          The Handler doesn't support the given/required captcha types.
          If this is used, the <tp:member-ref>CaptchaError</tp:member-ref>
          SHOULD be set to <tp:error-ref>CaptchaNotSupported</tp:error-ref>.
          This SHOULD also be used if
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="ofdT.Channel">Close</tp:dbus-ref> is called
          before <tp:member-ref>CancelCaptcha</tp:member-ref>.
          <tp:rationale>
            If no Handler supports captcha channels,
            the ChannelDispatcher will just call
            <tp:dbus-ref namespace="ofdT.Channel">Close</tp:dbus-ref>,
            because it has no knowledge of specific channel types.
          </tp:rationale>
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Service_Confused" value="2">
        <tp:docstring>
          The Handler doesn't understand the captcha data received. The
          challenger may be sending gibberish.
          If this is used, the <tp:member-ref>CaptchaError</tp:member-ref>
          SHOULD be set to <tp:error-ref>ServiceConfused</tp:error-ref>.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
    </tp:enum>

    <tp:enum name="Captcha_Status" type="u" plural="Captcha_Statuses">
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Local_Pending" value="0">
        <tp:docstring>
          The challenge/response exchange is in progress and waiting for
          a local action. Call <tp:member-ref>AnswerCaptchas</tp:member-ref>
          to go to the Remote_Pending state, or call
          <tp:member-ref>CancelCaptcha</tp:member-ref> followed by 
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="ofdT.Channel">Close</tp:dbus-ref>
          to give up.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Remote_Pending" value="1">
        <tp:docstring>
          The challenge/response exchange is in progress and waiting for
          a response from the server. Wait for a reply from the server,
          which will result in the Succeeded, Try_Again, or Failed state,
          or call <tp:member-ref>CancelCaptcha</tp:member-ref> followed by
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="ofdT.Channel">Close</tp:dbus-ref>
          to give up.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Succeeded" value="2">
        <tp:docstring>
          Everyone is happy. Connection to the server will proceed as soon as
          this state is reached. There is nothing useful to do in this state
          except to call <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="ofdT.Channel">Close</tp:dbus-ref>
          to close the channel.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Try_Again" value="3">
        <tp:docstring>
          The server has indicated an authentication failure.
          Call <tp:member-ref>GetCaptchas</tp:member-ref> again to get
          a new captcha, or
          <tp:member-ref>CancelCaptcha</tp:member-ref> followed by
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="ofdT.Channel">Close</tp:dbus-ref>
          to give up.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
      <tp:enumvalue suffix="Failed" value="4">
        <tp:docstring>
          Authentication has failed in some way. There is nothing
          useful to do in this state except to close the channel with
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="ofdT.Channel">Close</tp:dbus-ref>.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:enumvalue>
    </tp:enum>

  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
