<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Client_Handler"
  xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright>Copyright (C) 2008 Collabora Ltd.</tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright>Copyright (C) 2008 Nokia Corporation</tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
      modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
      License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
      version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

    <p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
      but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
      MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
      Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

    <p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
      License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
      Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA
      02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>

  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Client.Handler.DRAFT"
    tp:causes-havoc="experimental">
    <tp:added version="0.17.12">(as a draft)</tp:added>

    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Client.DRAFT"/>

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>Channel handlers are the eventual handler for a channel or a
        channel bundle; a typical channel handler is a user interface
        process handling channels of a particular type.</p>

      <p>When a new incoming channel (one with
        <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel">Requested</tp:dbus-ref>
        = FALSE) is offered to
        <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Client">Approver</tp:dbus-ref>s
        by the channel dispatcher, it also offers the Approvers a list of all
        the running or activatable handlers whose
        <tp:member-ref>HandlerChannelFilter</tp:member-ref> property
        (possibly as cached in the .client file) indicates that they
        are able to handle the channel. The Approvers can choose one of
        those channel handlers to handle the channel.</p>

      <p>When a new outgoing channel (one with
        <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Channel">Requested</tp:dbus-ref>
        = TRUE) appears, the channel dispatcher passes it to an appropriate
        channel handler automatically.
      </p>

    </tp:docstring>

    <property name="HandlerChannelFilter"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Handler_Channel_Filter"
      type="aa{sv}" access="read" tp:type="Channel_Class[]">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>A specification of the channels that this channel handler can
          deal with. It will be offered to approvers as a potential
          channel handler for bundles that contain only suitable channels,
          or for suitable channels that must be handled separately.</p>

        <p>This property works in exactly the same way as the
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Client.Observer.DRAFT.ObserverChannelFilter</tp:dbus-ref>
          property. In the .client file, it is represented in the
          same way as ObserverChannelFilter, but the group has the same
          name as this interface and the keys start with
          HandlerChannelFilter instead of ObserverChannelFilter.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <property name="BypassApproval" tp:name-for-bindings="Bypass_Approval"
      type="b" access="read">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>If true, channels destined for this handler are automatically
          handled, without invoking approvers.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>The intended usage is to allow a client handling one channel to
            pick up closely related channels. Suppose a client capable of
            handling both Text and StreamedMedia,
            <code>org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Client.Empathy</code>, is
            handling a StreamedMedia channel. That client can take a second
            well-known bus name, say
            <code>org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Client.Empathy._1._42.Bundle1</code>,
            and configure an object at
            <code>/org/freedesktop/Telepathy/Client/Empathy/_1/_42/Bundle1</code>
            with BypassApproval = TRUE,
            whose <tp:member-ref>HandlerChannelFilter</tp:member-ref>
            matches closely related Text channels by their Bundle property.
            (This is use-case dis5)</p>
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <method name="HandleChannels" tp:name-for-bindings="Handle_Channels">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Called by the channel dispatcher when this client should handle these
          channels, or when this client should present channels that it is already
          handling to the user (e.g. bring them into the foreground).</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>Clients are expected to know what channels they're already handling,
            and which channel object path corresponds to which window or tab.
            This can easily be done using a hash table keyed by channels' object
            paths.</p>
        </tp:rationale>

        <p>This method can raise any D-Bus error. If it does, or if the
          handler loses its bus name before all the channels have closed, the
          handler is assumed to have failed or crashed, and the channel
          dispatcher MUST recover in an implementation-specific way.</p>

        <p>It is RECOMMENDED that the channel dispatcher attempts to
          close the channels using
          <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Channel.Close</tp:dbus-ref>,
          but resorts to calling
          <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Channel.Interface.Destroyable.Destroy</tp:dbus-ref>
          (if available) or ignoring the channel (if not) if the same handler
          repeatedly fails to handle channels.</p>
      </tp:docstring>

      <arg name="Account" type="o" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          The
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Account</tp:dbus-ref>
          with which the channels are associated. The
          well-known bus name to use is that of the
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">AccountManager</tp:dbus-ref>.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg name="Connection" type="o" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          The Connection with which the channels are associated. The
          well-known bus name to use can be derived from this object
          path by removing the leading '/' and replacing all subsequent
          '/' by '.'.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg name="Channels" type="a(oa{sv})" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          The channels and their immutable properties. Their well-known
          bus name is the same as that of the Connection.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg name="Requests_Satisfied" type="ao" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          The requests satisfied by these channels.

          <tp:rationale>
            There can be more than one, if they were EnsureChannel
            requests.
          </tp:rationale>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg name="User_Action_Time" type="t" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          The time at which user action occurred, or 0 if this channel
          is to be handled for some reason not involving user action.
          Handlers SHOULD use this for focus-stealing prevention,
          if applicable.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <!-- FIXME: invent a way to say "any error is possible" in spec markup -->
    </method>

    <method name="AddRequest" tp:name-for-bindings="Add_Request">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Called by the ChannelDispatcher to indicate that channels have been
          requested, and that if the request is successful, they will be
          handled by this Handler.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>This allows the UI to start preparing to handle the channels
            in advance (e.g. render a window with an "in progress" message),
            improving perceived responsiveness.</p>
        </tp:rationale>

        <p>(FIXME: how do we know the returned channels will be handled by
          this handler? Do we just assume that they'll match the
          HandlerChannelFilter iff the request does?)</p>
      </tp:docstring>

      <arg name="Request" type="o" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          The <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">ChannelRequest</tp:dbus-ref>
          object, which MUST have been returned by <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.ChannelDispatcher.DRAFT">CreateChannel</tp:dbus-ref>
          or <tp:dbus-ref
            namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.ChannelDispatcher.DRAFT">EnsureChannel</tp:dbus-ref>
          before this method is called.

          <tp:rationale>
            See those methods for the rationale of this ordering.
          </tp:rationale>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg name="Properties" type="a{sv}"
        tp:type="Qualified_Property_Value_Map" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          <p>Some of the properties of the ChannelRequest. To avoid race
            conditions, this dictionary MUST NOT include properties whose
            values could subsequently change. It SHOULD include as many
            properties as possible, given that constraint.</p>

          <p>In particular, the properties <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.ChannelRequest.DRAFT">Requests</tp:dbus-ref>
            and <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.ChannelRequest.DRAFT">UserActionTime</tp:dbus-ref>
            MUST be included.</p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
    </method>

    <method name="RemoveFailedRequest"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Remove_Failed_Request">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Called by the ChannelDispatcher to indicate that a request
          previously passed to <tp:member-ref>AddRequest</tp:member-ref>
          has failed and should be disregarded.</p>
      </tp:docstring>

      <arg name="Request" type="o" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          The request that failed.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg name="Error" type="s" tp:type="DBus_Error_Name" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          <p>The name of the D-Bus error with which the request failed.</p>

          <p>If this is <code>org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Errors.NotYours</code>,
            this indicates that the request succeeded, but all the resulting
            channels were given to some other handler.</p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg name="Message" type="s" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          Any message supplied with the D-Bus error.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
    </method>

    <property name="HandledChannels" tp:name-for-bindings="Handled_Channels"
      type="ao" access="read">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>A list of the channels that this Handler is currently handling.
        </p>

        <p>There is no change notification.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>This property exists for state recovery - it makes it possible
            for channel handling to survive a ChannelDispatcher crash.</p>

          <p>If the channel dispatcher is automatically replaced, the
            replacement can discover all Handlers by looking for the Client
            well-known bus names, and discover which channels they are
            currently handling. Once this has been done, all unhandled
            channels can be re-dispatched, and the only issue visible to
            the user is that unhandled channels that they have already
            approved might be sent back to Approvers.</p>
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
