<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Client_Approver"
  xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright>Copyright © 2008-2009 Collabora Ltd.</tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright>Copyright © 2008-2009 Nokia Corporation</tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
      modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
      License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
      version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

    <p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
      but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
      MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
      Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

    <p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
      License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
      Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA
      02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>

  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Client.Approver">
    <tp:added version="0.17.26">(as a stable interface)</tp:added>

    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Client"/>

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>Approvers are clients that notify the user that new channels have
        been created by a contact, and allow the user to accept or reject
        those channels. The new channels are represented by a <tp:dbus-ref
          namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">ChannelDispatchOperation</tp:dbus-ref>
        object, which is passed to the
        <tp:member-ref>AddDispatchOperation</tp:member-ref> method.</p>

      <tp:rationale>
        <p>For instance, Empathy's tray icon, or the answer/reject window
          seen when a Maemo device receives a VoIP call, should be
          Approvers.</p>
      </tp:rationale>

      <p>Approvers can also select which channel handler will be used for the
        channel, for instance by offering the user a list of possible
        handlers rather than just an accept/reject choice.
        However, the Channel Dispatcher must be able to prioritize
        possible handlers on its own using some reasonable heuristic,
        probably based on user configuration.</p>

      <p>It is possible (and useful) to have an approver and
        a channel handler in the same process; this is particularly useful
        if a channel handler wants to claim responsibility for particular
        channels itself.</p>

      <p>All approvers are notified simultaneously. For instance, in a
        desktop system, there might be one approver that displays a
        notification-area icon, one that is part of a contact list
        window and highlights contacts there, and one that is part
        of a full-screen media player.</p>

      <p>Any approver can approve the handling of a channel dispatch operation
        with a particular channel handler by calling the <tp:dbus-ref
          namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.ChannelDispatchOperation">HandleWith</tp:dbus-ref>
        method. Approvers can also attempt to <tp:dbus-ref
          namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.ChannelDispatchOperation">Claim</tp:dbus-ref>
        channels; if this succeeds, the approver may handle the channels
        itself (if it is also a Handler), or close the channels in order to
        reject them.</p>

      <p>At the D-Bus level, there is no "reject" operation: approvers wishing
        to reject channels SHOULD call the Claim method, then (if it succeeds)
        close the channels in any way they see fit.</p>

      <p>The first approver to reply gets its decision acted on; any other
        approvers that reply at approximately the same time will get a D-Bus
        error, indicating that the channel has already been dealt with.</p>

      <p>Approvers should usually prompt the user and ask for
        confirmation, rather than dispatching the channel to a handler
        straight away.</p>

      <p>Non-interactive approvers can also be implemented as
        <tp:dbus-ref namespace="ofdT.Client">Observer</tp:dbus-ref>s as
        described in the interface description.</p>
    </tp:docstring>

    <property name="ApproverChannelFilter"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Approver_Channel_Filter"
      type="aa{sv}" access="read" tp:type="Channel_Class[]">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>A specification of the channels in which this approver is
          interested. The <tp:member-ref>AddDispatchOperation</tp:member-ref>
          method should be called by the channel dispatcher whenever at least
          one of the channels in a channel dispatch operation matches this
          description.</p>

        <p>This property works in exactly the same way as the
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Client.Observer.ObserverChannelFilter</tp:dbus-ref>
          property. In particular, it cannot change while the approver process
          continues to own the corresponding Client bus name.</p>

        <p>In the .client file, it is represented in the
          same way as ObserverChannelFilter, but the group has the same
          name as this interface and the keys start with
          ApproverChannelFilter instead of ObserverChannelFilter.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <method name="AddDispatchOperation"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Add_Dispatch_Operation">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Called by the channel dispatcher when a ChannelDispatchOperation
          in which the approver has registered an interest is created,
          or when the approver starts up while such channel dispatch
          operations already exist.</p>

        <p>The channel dispatcher SHOULD call this method on all approvers
          at the same time. If an approver returns an error from this method,
          the approver is assumed to be faulty.</p>

        <p>If no approvers return from this method
          successfully (including situations where there are no matching
          approvers at all), the channel dispatcher SHOULD consider this
          to be an error, and recover by dispatching the channel to the
          most preferred handler.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          Processes that aren't approvers (or don't at least ensure that there
          is some approver) probably shouldn't be making connections
          anyway, so there should always be at least one approver running.
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>

      <arg name="Channels" direction="in"
        type="a(oa{sv})" tp:type="Channel_Details[]">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          <p>The initial value of the <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">ChannelDispatchOperation.Channels</tp:dbus-ref>
            property, containing the <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Channel</tp:dbus-ref>s
            to be dispatched and their properties.</p>

          <tp:rationale>
            <p>This can't be signalled to the approver through the Properties
              parameter of this method, because Channels is not an immutable
              property.</p>
          </tp:rationale>

          <p>This argument always contains all of the channels in the channel
            dispatch operation, even if not all of them actually match
            the <tp:member-ref>ApproverChannelFilter</tp:member-ref>.</p>

          <tp:rationale>
            <p>This seems the least bad way to handle such a situation;
              see the discussion on
              <a href="http://bugs.freedesktop.org/show_bug.cgi?id=21090">bug
                #21090</a>.</p>
          </tp:rationale>

          <p>The actual channels to be dispatched may reduce as channels are
            closed: this is signalled by <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">ChannelDispatchOperation.ChannelLost</tp:dbus-ref>.
          </p>

          <p>Approvers SHOULD connect to ChannelLost and <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">ChannelDispatchOperation.Finished</tp:dbus-ref>.
            (if desired) before returning from AddDispatchOperation, since
            those signals are guaranteed not to be emitted until after all
            AddDispatchOperation calls have returned (with success or failure)
            or timed out.</p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg name="DispatchOperation" type="o" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          <p>The
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">ChannelDispatchOperation</tp:dbus-ref>
            to be processed.</p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg name="Properties" type="a{sv}"
        tp:type="Qualified_Property_Value_Map" direction="in">
        <tp:docstring>
          <p>Properties of the channel dispatch operation. The keys MUST be
            fully qualified D-Bus property names. This MUST NOT include
            properties that could change, SHOULD include as many properties as
            possible given that constraint, and MUST include at least the
            <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.ChannelDispatchOperation">Account</tp:dbus-ref>,
            <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.ChannelDispatchOperation">Connection</tp:dbus-ref>
            and <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.ChannelDispatchOperation">PossibleHandlers</tp:dbus-ref>
            properties.</p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
    </method>

  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
