<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Connection_Interface_Capabilities" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2005, 2006 Collabora Limited </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2005, 2006 Nokia Corporation </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2006 INdT </tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.Capabilities">
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection"/>

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>An interface for connections where it is possible to know what channel
        types may be requested before the request is made to the connection
        object. Each capability represents a commitment by the connection
        manager that it will ordinarily be able to create a channel when given
        a request with the given type and handle.</p>

      <p>Capabilities pertain to particular contact handles, and represent
        activities such as having a text chat or a voice call with the user.
        The activities are represented by the D-Bus interface name of the
        channel type for that activity.</p>

      <p>The generic capability flags are defined by
        <tp:type>Connection_Capability_Flags</tp:type>.</p>

      <p>In addition, channel types may have type specific capability flags of
        their own, which are described in the documentation for each channel
        type.</p>

      <p>This interface also provides for user interfaces notifying the
        connection manager of what capabilities to advertise for the user. This
        is done by using the AdvertiseCapabilities method, and deals with the
        interface names of channel types and the type specific flags pertaining
        to them which are implemented by available client processes.</p>
    </tp:docstring>

    <tp:changed version="0.17.8">Previously, this interface
      also expressed capabilities of the connection itself, indicating what
      sorts of channels could be requested (for instance, the ability to
      open chatroom lists or chatrooms). However, this was never very
      well-defined or consistent, and as far as we know it was never
      implemented correctly. This usage is now deprecated.</tp:changed>

    <!-- FIXME: are the type-specific flags sufficient, in a world that has
    the Requests interface? It'd be nice if we could advertise capabilities
    that are not defined in terms of a channel type but rather in terms of
    a property or something, e.g. Channel.Interface.TLS.Secure for
    individually TLS'd channels. -->

    <tp:flags name="Connection_Capability_Flags"
      value-prefix="Connection_Capability_Flag" type="u">
      <tp:flag suffix="Create" value="1">
        <tp:docstring>
          The given channel type and handle can be given to RequestChannel to
          create a new channel of this type.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
      <tp:flag suffix="Invite" value="2">
        <tp:docstring>
          The given contact can be invited to an existing channel of this type.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
    </tp:flags>

    <tp:struct name="Capability_Pair" array-name="Capability_Pair_List">
      <tp:docstring>A pair (channel type, type-specific flags) as passed to
        AdvertiseCapabilities on the Capabilities interface.</tp:docstring>
      <tp:member type="s" tp:type="DBus_Interface" name="Channel_Type"/>
      <tp:member type="u" name="Type_Specific_Flags"/>
    </tp:struct>

    <tp:struct name="Contact_Capability" array-name="Contact_Capability_List">
      <tp:docstring>A struct (contact handle, channel type, generic flags,
        type-specific flags) representing a capability posessed by a contact,
        as returned by GetCapabilities on the Capabilities
        interface.</tp:docstring>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Contact_Handle" name="Handle"/>
      <tp:member type="s" tp:type="DBus_Interface" name="Channel_Type"/>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Connection_Capability_Flags"
                 name="Generic_Flags"/>
      <tp:member type="u" name="Type_Specific_Flags"/>
    </tp:struct>

    <tp:struct name="Capability_Change" array-name="Capability_Change_List">
      <tp:docstring>A struct (contact handle, channel type, old generic flags,
        new generic flags, old type-specific flags, new type-specific flags)
        representing a change to one of a contact's capabilities, as seen in the
        CapabilitiesChanged signal on the Capabilities interface.</tp:docstring>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Contact_Handle" name="Handle"/>
      <tp:member type="s" tp:type="DBus_Interface" name="Channel_Type"/>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Connection_Capability_Flags"
                 name="Old_Generic_Flags"/>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Connection_Capability_Flags"
                 name="New_Generic_Flags"/>
      <tp:member type="u" name="Old_Type_Specific_Flags"/>
      <tp:member type="u" name="New_Type_Specific_Flags"/>
    </tp:struct>

    <method name="AdvertiseCapabilities"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Advertise_Capabilities">
      <arg direction="in" name="Add" type="a(su)" tp:type="Capability_Pair[]">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          An array of structures containing:
          <ul>
            <li>a string channel type</li>
            <li>a bitwise OR of type specific capability flags</li>
          </ul>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="Remove" type="as" tp:type="DBus_Interface[]">
        <tp:docstring>
          An array of D-Bus interface names of channel types to remove
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="a(su)" tp:type="Capability_Pair[]">
        <tp:docstring>
          An array of structures describing the current capabilities containing:
          <ul>
            <li>a string channel type</li>
            <li>a bitwise OR of type specific capability flags</li>
          </ul>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Used by user interfaces to indicate which channel types they are able
        to handle on this connection. Because these may be provided by
        different client processes, this method accepts channel types to add
        and remove from the set already advertised on this connection. The type
        of advertised capabilities (create versus invite) is protocol-dependent
        and hence cannot be set by the this method. In the case of a client
        adding an already advertised channel type but with new channel type
        specific flags, the connection manager should simply add the new flags
        to the set of advertised capabilities.</p>

        <p>Upon a successful invocation of this method, the CapabilitiesChanged
        signal will be emitted for the user's own handle (as returned by
        GetSelfHandle) by the connection manager to indicate the changes
        that have been made.  This signal should also be monitored to ensure
        that the set is kept accurate - for example, a client may remove
        capabilities or type specific capability flags when it exits
        which are still provided by another client.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.Disconnected"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <signal name="CapabilitiesChanged"
      tp:name-for-bindings="Capabilities_Changed">
      <arg name="Caps" type="a(usuuuu)" tp:type="Capability_Change[]">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          An array of structures containing:
          <ul>
            <li>an integer handle representing the contact</li>
            <li>a string channel type</li>
            <li>a bitwise OR of the contact's old generic capability flags</li>
            <li>a bitwise OR of the contact's new generic capability flags</li>
            <li>a bitwise OR of the contact's old type specific capability flags</li>
            <li>a bitwise OR of the contact's new type specific capability flags</li>
          </ul>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Announce that there has been a change of capabilities on the
          given handle.</p>

        <p>If the handle is zero, the capabilities refer to the connection
          itself, in some poorly defined way. This usage is deprecated and
          clients should ignore it.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
    </signal>

    <method name="GetCapabilities" tp:name-for-bindings="Get_Capabilities">
      <arg direction="in" name="Handles" type="au" tp:type="Contact_Handle[]">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          <p>An array of contact handles for this connection.</p>

          <p>This may include zero, which originally meant a query for
            capabilities available on the connection itself. This usage
            is deprecated; clients SHOULD NOT do this, and connection managers
            SHOULD proceed as though zero had not been present in this
            list.</p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="a(usuu)" tp:type="Contact_Capability[]">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          An array of structures containing:
          <ul>
            <li>an integer handle representing the contact</li>
            <li>a string channel type</li>
            <li>a bitwise OR of generic capability flags for the type</li>
            <li>a bitwise OR of type specific capability flags for the type</li>
          </ul>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Returns an array of capabilities for the given contact handles.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.Disconnected"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidHandle">
          <tp:docstring>
            The handle does not represent a contact and is not zero
          </tp:docstring>
        </tp:error>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.PermissionDenied"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
