<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Connection_Manager" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright>Copyright (C) 2005, 2006 Collabora Limited</tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright>Copyright (C) 2005, 2006 Nokia Corporation</tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright>Copyright (C) 2006 INdT</tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.ConnectionManager">

    <tp:simple-type name="Connection_Manager_Name" type="s">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The name of a connection manager, found in its well-known
          bus name and object path. This must be a non-empty string of
          ASCII letters, digits and underscores, starting with a letter.
          This is typically the name of the executable with any "telepathy-"
          prefix removed, and any hyphen/minus signs replaced by
          underscores.</p>

        <p>Connection manager names SHOULD NOT be the same as the name of
          the protocol they implement.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>This is likely to lead to conflicts between different
            implementations of the same protocol (or indeed inability
            to distinguish between the different implementations!). The
            Telepathy project traditionally uses some sort of pun (Haze is
            based on libpurple, Salut implements a protocol often called
            Bonjour, and Wilde implements the OSCAR protocol).</p>
        </tp:rationale>

        <p>Connection manager names SHOULD NOT be the same as the name of
          a library on which they are based.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>We often abbreviate, for instance, telepathy-haze as "Haze",
            but abbreviating telepathy-sofiasip to "Sofia-SIP" would cause
            confusion between the connection manager and the library it
            uses. Please don't repeat that mistake.</p>
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:changed version="0.17.1">Prior to version 0.17.1, the allowed
        characters were not specified</tp:changed>
    </tp:simple-type>

    <tp:simple-type name="Protocol" type="s">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>An instant messaging protocol. It must consist only of ASCII
          letters, digits and hyphen/minus signs (U+002D "-"), and must start
          with a letter. Where possible, this SHOULD be
          chosen from the following well-known values:</p>

        <ul>
          <li>aim - AOL Instant Messenger (OSCAR or TOC)</li>
          <li>gadugadu - Gadu-Gadu</li>
          <li>groupwise - Novell Groupwise</li>
          <li>icq - ICQ (OSCAR)</li>
          <li>irc - Internet Relay Chat (RFC 1459, 2810-2813)</li>
          <li>jabber - XMPP (RFC 3920, 3921) or Jabber</li>
          <li>local-xmpp - Link-local XMPP (XEP-0174) (Bonjour, Salut)</li>
          <li>msn - MSNP (Windows Live Messenger)</li>
          <li>myspace - MySpaceIM</li>
          <li>napster - Napster</li>
          <li>qq - Tencent QQ</li>
          <li>sametime - IBM Lotus Sametime</li>
          <li>silc - SILC</li>
          <li>sip - Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)</li>
          <li>trepia - Trepia</li>
          <li>yahoo - YMSG (Yahoo! Messenger)</li>
          <li>zephyr - Zephyr</li>
        </ul>
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:changed version="0.17.1">Prior to version 0.17.1, the allowed
        characters were not specified</tp:changed>
    </tp:simple-type>

    <tp:struct name="Param_Spec" array-name="Param_Spec_List">
      <tp:docstring>A struct representing an allowed parameter, as returned
        by GetParameters on the ConnectionManager interface.</tp:docstring>
      <tp:member type="s" name="Name">
        <tp:docstring>A string parameter name</tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Conn_Mgr_Param_Flags" name="Flags">
        <tp:docstring>A bitwise OR of the parameter flags</tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="s" tp:type="DBus_Signature" name="Signature">
        <tp:docstring>A string containing the D-Bus type signature
          for this parameter</tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="v" name="Default_Value">
        <tp:docstring>The default value (if the Has_Default flag is not
          present, there is no default and this takes some dummy value,
          which SHOULD be of the appropriate D-Bus type)</tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
    </tp:struct>

    <tp:flags name="Conn_Mgr_Param_Flags" value-prefix="Conn_Mgr_Param_Flag" type="u">
      <tp:flag suffix="Required" value="1">
        <tp:docstring>
          This parameter is required for connecting to the server.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
      <tp:flag suffix="Register" value="2">
        <tp:docstring>
          This parameter is required for registering an account on the
          server.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
      <tp:flag suffix="Has_Default" value="4">
        <tp:docstring>
          This parameter has a default value, which is returned in
          GetParameters; not providing this parameter is equivalent to
          providing the default.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
      <tp:flag suffix="Secret" value="8">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          <p>This parameter should be considered private or secret; for
            instance, clients should store it in a "password safe" like
            gnome-keyring or kwallet, omit it from debug logs, and use a
            text input widget that hides the value of the parameter.</p>

          <p>(Clients that support older connection managers may also treat
            any parameter whose name contains "password" as though it had this
            flag.)</p>
        </tp:docstring>
        <tp:added version="0.17.2"/>
      </tp:flag>
    </tp:flags>

    <method name="GetParameters" tp:name-for-bindings="Get_Parameters">
      <arg direction="in" name="Protocol" type="s" tp:type="Protocol">
        <tp:docstring>
          The required protocol name
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="a(susv)" tp:type="Param_Spec[]">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          An array of structs representing possible parameters.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Get a list of the parameters which must or may be provided to the
        RequestConnection method when connecting to the given protocol,
        or registering (the boolean &quot;register&quot; parameter is available,
        and set to true).
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotImplemented">
          The requested protocol is not supported by this manager
        </tp:error>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <method name="ListProtocols" tp:name-for-bindings="List_Protocols">
      <arg direction="out" type="as" tp:type="Protocol[]">
        <tp:docstring>
          A array of string protocol identifiers supported by this manager
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Get a list of protocol identifiers that are implemented by this
        connection manager.
      </tp:docstring>
    </method>

    <signal name="NewConnection" tp:name-for-bindings="New_Connection">
      <arg name="Bus_Name" type="s" tp:type="DBus_Bus_Name">
        <tp:docstring>
          The D-Bus service where the connection object can be found
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="Object_Path" type="o">
        <tp:docstring>
          The object path of the Connection object on this service
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="Protocol" type="s" tp:type="Protocol">
        <tp:docstring>
          The identifier for the protocol this connection uses
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Emitted when a new Connection object is created.
      </tp:docstring>
    </signal>

    <method name="RequestConnection" tp:name-for-bindings="Request_Connection">
      <arg direction="in" name="Protocol" type="s" tp:type="Protocol">
        <tp:docstring>
          The protocol identifier
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="Parameters" type="a{sv}"
        tp:type="String_Variant_Map">
        <tp:docstring>
          A dictionary mapping parameter name to the variant boxed value
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="s" tp:type="DBus_Bus_Name">
        <tp:docstring>
          A D-Bus service name where the new Connection object can be found
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="o">
        <tp:docstring>
          The D-Bus object path to the Connection on this service
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Request a
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Connection</tp:dbus-ref>
          object representing a given account on a given
          protocol with the given parameters. The method returns the bus name
          and the object path where the new Connection object can be found,
          which should have the status of Connection_Status_Disconnected, to
          allow signal handlers to be attached before connecting is started
          with the
          <tp:dbus-ref namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection">Connect</tp:dbus-ref>
          method.</p>

        <p>The parameters which must and may be provided in the parameters
        dictionary can be discovered with the GetParameters method. These
        parameters, their types, and their default values may be cached
        in files so that all available connection managers do not need to be
        started to discover which protocols are available.</p>

        <p>To request values for these parameters from the user, a client must
        have prior knowledge of the meaning of the parameter names, so the
        following well-known names and types should be used where appropriate:</p>

        <dl>
          <dt>s:account</dt>
          <dd>The identifier for the user's account on the server</dd>

          <dt>s:server</dt><dd>A fully qualified domain name or numeric IPv4 or IPv6
        address. Using the fully-qualified domain name form is recommended
        whenever possible. If this parameter is specified and the account
        for that protocol also specifies a server, this parameter should
        override that in the user id.</dd>

      <dt>q:port</dt><dd>A TCP or UDP port number. If this parameter is specified
        and the account for that protocol also specifies a port, this
        parameter should override that in the account.</dd>

      <dt>s:password</dt><dd>A password associated with the account.</dd>

      <dt>b:require-encryption</dt><dd>Require encryption for this connection. A
        connection should fail to connect if require-encryption is set
        and an encrypted connection is not possible.</dd>

      <dt>b:register</dt><dd>This account should be created on the server if it
        does not already exist.</dd>

      <dt>s:ident</dt><dd>The local username to report to the server if
        necessary, such as in IRC.</dd>

      <dt>s:fullname</dt><dd>The user's full name if the service requires this
        when authenticating or registering.</dd>

      <dt>s:stun-server</dt><dd>The IP address or FQDN of a STUN server to use
        for NAT traversal, without any ":port" suffix.</dd>
      <dt>q:stun-port</dt><dd>The UDP port number on the stun-server to use for
        STUN. Only significant if the stun-server is also supplied.</dd>
        </dl>

        <p>Every successful RequestConnection call will cause the emission of a
        NewConnection signal for the same newly created connection. The
        requester can use the returned object path and service name
        independently of the emission of that signal. In that case this signal
        emission is most useful for, e.g. other processes that are monitoring
        the creation of new connections.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotImplemented">
          The requested protocol is not supported by this manager
        </tp:error>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable">
          The requested connection already appears to exist
        </tp:error>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidArgument">
          Unrecognised connection parameters
        </tp:error>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <property name="Interfaces" tp:name-for-bindings="Interfaces"
      type="as" access="read">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>A list of the extra interfaces provided by this connection manager
          (i.e. extra functionality that can be provided even before a
          connection has been created).</p>

        <p>No interfaces suitable for listing in this property are currently
          defined; it's provided as a hook for possible future
          functionality.</p>

        <p>To be compatible with older connection managers, if retrieving
          this property fails, clients SHOULD assume that its value is
          an empty list.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:added version="0.17.8"/>
    </property>

    <!-- FIXME: One thing we could perhaps use Interfaces for would be a
    ConnectionManager.Interface.Capabilities that can give hints regarding
    the capabilities (in the sense of
    Connection.Interface.Requests.AvailableChannelClasses and/or
    Connection.GetInterfaces()) that a Connection from this CM is likely
    to have -->

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>A D-Bus service which allows connections to be created. The manager
      processes are intended to be started by D-Bus service activation.</p>

    <p>For service discovery, each Telepathy connection manager must have
      a <em>connection manager name</em> (see
      <tp:type>Connection_Manager_Name</tp:type> for syntax).</p>

    <p>The connection manager must then provide a well-known bus name of
      <code>org.freedesktop.Telepathy.ConnectionManager.<em>cmname</em></code>
      where <em>cmname</em> is its connection manager name. If it makes sense
      to start the connection manager using D-Bus service activation, it
      must register that well-known name for service activation by installing
      a .service file.</p>

    <p>Clients can list the running connection managers by calling the
      ListNames method on the D-Bus daemon's org.freedesktop.DBus interface
      and looking for names matching the above pattern; they can list the
      activatable connection managers by calling ListActivatableNames, and
      they should usually combine the two lists to get a complete list of
      running or activatable connection managers.</p>

    <p>When the connection manager is running, it must have an object
      implementing the ConnectionManager interface at the object path
      <code>/org/freedesktop/Telepathy/ConnectionManager/<em>cmname</em></code>.
    </p>

    <p>Connection managers' capabilities can be determined dynamically by
      calling their ListProtocols method, then for each protocol of interest,
      calling GetParameters to discover the required and optional parameters.
      However, since it is inefficient to activate all possible connection
      managers on the system just to find out what they can do, there
      is a standard mechanism to store static information about CMs in
      ".manager files".</p>

    <p>To look up a connection manager's supported protocols, clients
      should search the data directories specified by
      <a href="http://standards.freedesktop.org/basedir-spec/basedir-spec-latest.html">the
        freedesktop.org XDG Base Directory Specification</a> ($XDG_DATA_HOME,
      defaulting to $HOME/.local/share if unset, followed by
      colon-separated paths from $XDG_DATA_DIRS, defaulting to
      /usr/local/share:/usr/share if unset) for the first file named
      <code>telepathy/managers/<em>cmname</em>.manager</code> that can be
      read without error. This file has the same syntax as a
      <a href="http://standards.freedesktop.org/desktop-entry-spec/desktop-entry-spec-latest.html">freedesktop.org Desktop Entry file</a>.</p>

    <p>Clients must still support connection managers for which no
      <code>.manager</code> file can be found, which they can do by activating
      the connection manager and calling its methods; the
      <code>.manager</code> file is merely an optimization. Connection managers
      whose list of protocols can change at any time (for instance, via
      a plugin architecture) should not install a <code>.manager</code>
      file.</p>

    <p>For each protocol name <em>proto</em> that would be returned by
      ListProtocols, the .manager file contains a group
      headed <code>[Protocol <em>proto</em>]</code>. For each parameter
      <em>p</em> that would be returned by GetParameters(<em>proto</em>), the
      .manager file contains a key <code>param-<em>p</em></code> with a value
      consisting of a D-Bus signature (a single complete type), optionally
      followed by a space and a space-separated list of flags. The supported
      flags are:</p>

    <ul>
      <li><code>required</code>, corresponding to
        Conn_Mgr_Param_Flag_Required</li>
      <li><code>register</code>, corresponding
        to Conn_Mgr_Param_Flag_Register</li>
      <li><code>secret</code>, corresponding
        to Conn_Mgr_Param_Flag_Secret</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The group may also contain a key <code>default-<em>p</em></code>
      whose value is a string form of the default value for the parameter.
      If this key exists, it sets the default, and also sets the flag
      Conn_Mgr_Param_Flag_Has_Default. The default value is formatted
      according to the D-Bus signature as follows:</p>

    <dl>
      <dt>s (string)</dt>
        <dd>The UTF-8 string</dd>
      <dt>o (object path)</dt>
        <dd>The object path as an ASCII string</dd>
      <dt>b (boolean)</dt>
        <dd>"true" (case-insensitively) or "1" means True, "false"
          (case-insensitively) or "0" means False</dd>
      <dt>q, u, t (16-, 32-, 64-bit unsigned integer)</dt>
        <dd>ASCII decimal integer</dd>
      <dt>n, i, x (16-, 32-, 64-bit signed integer)</dt>
        <dd>ASCII decimal integer, optionally prefixed with "-"</dd>
      <dt>d (double-precision floating point)</dt>
        <dd>ASCII decimal number</dd>
    </dl>

    <p>Currently, no other D-Bus signatures are allowed to have default values,
      but clients parsing the .manager file MUST ignore defaults
      that they cannot parse, and treat them as if the
      <code>default-<em>p</em></code> key was not present at all.</p>

    <p>It is not required that a connection manager be able to support multiple
    protocols, or even multiple connections. When a connection is made, a
    service name where the connection object can be found is returned. A
    manager which can only make one connection may then remove itself from its
    well-known bus name, causing a new connection manager to be activated when
    somebody attempts to make a new connection.</p>
    </tp:docstring>

    <tp:changed version="0.17.2">Prior to version 0.17.2, support for
      CMs with no .manager file was not explicitly required.</tp:changed>
  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
