<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Connection_Interface_Avatars" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright>Copyright (C) 2005-2007 Collabora Limited</tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright>Copyright (C) 2005, 2006 Nokia Corporation</tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright>Copyright (C) 2006 INdT</tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.Avatars">
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection"/>

    <tp:mapping name="Avatar_Token_Map">
      <tp:docstring>A dictionary whose keys are contact handles and whose
        values are avatar tokens.</tp:docstring>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Contact_Handle" name="Handle"/>
      <tp:member type="s" name="Token"/>
    </tp:mapping>

    <signal name="AvatarUpdated">
      <arg name="contact" type="u" tp:type="Contact_Handle">
        <tp:docstring>
          An integer handle for the contact whose avatar has changed
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="new_avatar_token" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          Unique token for their new avatar
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Emitted when the avatar for a contact has been updated, or first
        discovered on this connection. If the token differs from the token
        associated with the client's cached avatar for this contact, the new
        avatar should be requested with RequestAvatars.
      </tp:docstring>
    </signal>
    <signal name="AvatarRetrieved">
      <arg name="contact" type="u" tp:type="Contact_Handle">
        <tp:docstring>
          The contact whose avatar has been retrieved
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="token" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          The token corresponding to the avatar
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="avatar" type="ay">
        <tp:docstring>
          An array of bytes containing the image data
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="type" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          A string containing the image MIME type (eg image/jpeg), or empty if
          unknown
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Emitted when the avatar for a contact has been retrieved.
      </tp:docstring>
    </signal>
    <method name="GetAvatarRequirements">
      <arg direction="out" type="as">
        <tp:docstring>
          An array of supported MIME types (eg image/jpeg)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="q">
        <tp:docstring>
          The minimum image width in pixels
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="q">
        <tp:docstring>
          The minimum image height in pixels
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="q">
        <tp:docstring>
          The maximum image width in pixels, or 0 if there is no limit
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="q">
        <tp:docstring>
          The maximum image height in pixels, or 0 if there is no limit
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="u">
        <tp:docstring>
          The maximum image size in bytes, or 0 if there is no limit
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Get the required format of avatars on this connection.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.Disconnected"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.PermissionDenied"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>
    <method name="GetAvatarTokens">
      <arg direction="in" name="contacts" type="au" tp:type="Contact_Handle[]">
        <tp:docstring>
        An array of handles representing contacts
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="as">
        <tp:docstring>
          An array of avatar tokens or empty strings (if no avatar is set) in the
          same order as the given array of contact handles
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Get the unique tokens for all of the given contacts' avatars.

        Using this method in new Telepathy clients is deprecated; use
        GetKnownAvatarTokens instead.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.Disconnected"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidArgument"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.PermissionDenied"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>
    <method name="GetKnownAvatarTokens">
      <arg direction="in" name="contacts" type="au" tp:type="Contact_Handle[]">
        <tp:docstring>
        An array of handles representing contacts
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="a{us}" tp:type="Avatar_Token_Map">
        <tp:docstring>
          A dictionary of handles mapped to avatar tokens, containing only
          the known avatar tokens.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Get the unique tokens for the given contacts' avatars. These tokens
        can be persisted across connections, and should be used by the client
        to check whether the avatars have been updated.  A CM must always have
        the tokens for the self handle if one is set (even if it is set to no
        avatar). Otherwise, only tokens that are already known are returned. An
        empty token means the given contact has no avatar.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.Disconnected"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidArgument"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.PermissionDenied"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>
    <method name="RequestAvatar">
      <arg direction="in" name="contact" type="u" tp:type="Contact_Handle">
        <tp:docstring>
          An integer handle for the contact to request the avatar for
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="ay">
        <tp:docstring>
          An array of bytes containing the image data
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
        A string containing the image MIME type (eg image/jpeg), or empty if
        unknown
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Request the avatar for a given contact. Using this method in new
        Telepathy clients is deprecated; use RequestAvatars instead.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.Disconnected"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidHandle"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.PermissionDenied"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable">
          <tp:docstring>
            The contact does not currently have an avatar.
          </tp:docstring>
        </tp:error>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>
    <method name="RequestAvatars">
      <arg direction="in" name="contacts" type="au"
        tp:type="Contact_Handle[]">
        <tp:docstring>
          The contacts to retrieve avatars for
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Request avatars for a number of contacts. The AvatarRetrieved signal
        is emitted for each avatar retrieved. If the handles are valid but
        retrieving an avatar fails (for any reason, including the contact not
        having an avatar) the AvatarRetrieved signal is not emitted for that
        contact.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.Disconnected"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidHandle"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>
    <method name="SetAvatar">
      <arg direction="in" name="avatar" type="ay">
        <tp:docstring>
          An array of bytes representing the avatar image data
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="mime_type" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          A string representing the image MIME type
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          The string token of the new avatar
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Set a new avatar image for this connection. The avatar image must
        respect the requirements obtained by GetAvatarRequirements.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.Disconnected"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidArgument"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.PermissionDenied"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>
    <method name="ClearAvatar">
      <tp:added version="0.15.0" />
      <tp:docstring>
        Remove the avatar image for this connection.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.Disconnected"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>
    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>An interface for requesting avatars for contacts on a given connection,
    receiving notification when avatars are changed, and publishing your own
    avatar.</p>

    <p>Avatars are identified by a unique (per contact) token which represents a
    hash or timestamp (depending on the protocol) of the contacts' avatar data.
    An empty token means that an avatar has not been set for this contact, and
    a changed token implies the contact's avatar has changed, but the strings
    should otherwise be considered opaque by clients.</p>

    <p>A client should use GetKnownAvatarTokens to request the tokens for the
    avatars of all the contacts it is interested in when it connects. The
    avatars can then be requested using RequestAvatars for the contacts.
    Clients should bind to the AvatarChanged signal and request a new copy of
    the avatar when a contacts' avatar token changes. Clients should cache the
    token and data of each contact's avatar between connections, to avoid
    repeatedly retrieving the same avatar.</p>

    <p>To publish an avatar, a client should use SetAvatar to provide an image
    which meets the requirements returned by the GetAvatarRequirements
    function. On some protocols the avatar is stored on the server, so setting
    the avatar is persistent, but on others it is transferred via a peer to
    peer mechanism, so needs to be set every connection. Hence, on every
    connection, clients should inspect the avatar token of the connection's
    self handle, and set the avatar if it is an empty string (and may
    optionally replace it if the token corresponds to a different avatar).</p>

    <p>To remove the published avatar on protocols which have persistent avatars,
    a client should use the ClearAvatar method. This method can safely be used
    even if there is no avatar for this connection.</p>
    </tp:docstring>
  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
