<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Connection_Interface_Aliasing" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2005, 2006 Collabora Limited </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2005, 2006 Nokia Corporation </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2006 INdT </tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.Aliasing">
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection"/>

    <tp:mapping name="Alias_Map" array-name="">
      <tp:docstring>A dictionary whose keys are contact handles and whose
        values are aliases.</tp:docstring>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Contact_Handle" name="Handle"/>
      <tp:member type="s" name="Alias"/>
    </tp:mapping>

    <tp:struct name="Alias_Pair" array-name="Alias_Pair_List">
      <tp:docstring>A pair (contact handle, alias) as seen in the AliasesChanged
        signal.</tp:docstring>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Contact_Handle" name="Handle"/>
      <tp:member type="s" name="Alias"/>
    </tp:struct>

    <signal name="AliasesChanged">
      <arg name="aliases" type="a(us)" tp:type="Alias_Pair[]">
        <!-- FIXME: if we break API, this could be an Alias_Map, a{us} -->
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          An array containing structs of:
          <ul>
            <li>the handle representing the contact</li>
            <li>the new alias</li>
          </ul>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Signal emitted when a contact's alias (or that of the user) is changed.
      </tp:docstring>
    </signal>
    <tp:flags name="Connection_Alias_Flags" value-prefix="Connection_Alias_Flag" type="u">
      <tp:flag suffix="User_Set" value="1">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          <p>The aliases of contacts on this connection may be changed by the
            user of the service, not just by the contacts themselves. This is
            the case on Jabber, for instance.</p>
          <p>It is possible that aliases can be changed by the contacts too -
            which alias takes precedence is not defined by this
            specification, and depends on the server and/or connection manager
            implementation.</p>
          <p>This flag only applies to the aliases of "globally valid" contact
            handles. At this time, clients should not expect to be able to
            change the aliases corresponding to any channel-specific
            handles. If this becomes possible in future, a new flag will
            be defined.</p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:flag>
    </tp:flags>
    <method name="GetAliasFlags">
      <arg direction="out" type="u" tp:type="Connection_Alias_Flags">
        <tp:docstring>
          An integer with a bitwise OR of flags from ConnectionAliasFlags
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Return a bitwise OR of flags detailing the behaviour of aliases on this
        connection.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.Disconnected"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>
    <method name="RequestAliases">
      <arg direction="in" name="contacts" type="au" tp:type="Contact_Handle[]">
        <tp:docstring>
          An array of handles representing contacts
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" type="as">
        <tp:docstring>
          A list of aliases in the same order as the contact handles
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Request the value of several contacts' aliases at once.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.Disconnected"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidHandle"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>
    <method name="SetAliases">
      <arg direction="in" name="aliases" type="a{us}" tp:type="Alias_Map">
        <tp:docstring>
          A dictionary mapping integer handles of contacts
          to strings of the new alias to set.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Request that the alias of the given contact be changed. Success will be
        indicated by emitting an AliasesChanged signal. On connections where the
        CONNECTION_ALIAS_FLAG_USER_SET flag is not set, this method will only
        ever succeed if the contact is the user's own handle (as returned by
        GetSelfHandle on the Connection interface).
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.Disconnected"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidArgument"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.PermissionDenied"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>
    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>An interface on connections to support protocols where contacts have an
    alias which they can change at will. Provides a method for the user to set
    their own alias, and a signal which should be emitted when a contact's
    alias is changed or first discovered.</p>

    <p>On connections where the user is allowed to set aliases for contacts and
    store them on the server, the GetAliasFlags method will have the
    CONNECTION_ALIAS_FLAG_USER_SET flag set, and the SetAliases method
    may be called on contact handles other than the user themselves.</p>

    <p>Aliases are intended to be used as the main displayed name for the
    contact, where available.</p>
    </tp:docstring>
  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
