<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Connection_Interface_IRC_Command1" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2013 Collabora Limited </tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.IRCCommand1"
    tp:causes-havoc='not well-tested'>
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection"/>
    <tp:added version="0.27.3"/>

    <method name="Send" tp:name-for-bindings="Send">
      <arg direction="in" name="Command" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          The command followed by its arguments.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Send an arbitrary IRC command to the server.</p>
        <p>For example, an IRC client receiving <code>/bip blreset</code> from
           the user might call this method with <code>BIP blreset</code> as
           argument which will send <code>BIP blreset</code> to the server.</p>
        <p>The command is supplied in UTF-8 (because strings on D-Bus are
           always UTF-8). It is transcoded into the connection's configured
           character set, if different, before sending to the server.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.Disconnected"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidArgument">
          <tp:docstring>
            The connection manager MAY raise this error for commands that
            have a more appropriate D-Bus API.
          </tp:docstring>
        </tp:error>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>
    <tp:docstring>
      An interface to send arbitrary IRC commands to the server.
    </tp:docstring>
  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
