<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Connection_Interface_Sidecars1"
  xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0"
  >
  <tp:copyright>Copyright © 2009-2013 Collabora Limited</tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright>Copyright © 2009 Nokia Corporation</tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301,
USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.Sidecars1">
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection"/>
    <tp:added version="0.27.3"/>

    <method name="EnsureSidecar" tp:name-for-bindings="Ensure_Sidecar">
      <tp:added version="0.27.3">(as stable API)</tp:added>

      <arg direction="in" name="Main_Interface" type="s"
           tp:type="DBus_Interface">
        <tp:docstring>
          The "primary" interface implemented by an object attached
          to a connection. For example, a Gabble plugin implementing
          fine-grained control of XEP-0016 privacy lists might expose an object
          implementing <tt>com.example.PrivacyLists</tt>.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <arg direction="out" name="Path" type="o">
        <tp:docstring>The object path of the sidecar, exported by the same bus
          name as the Connection to which it is attached.</tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" name="Properties" type="a{sv}"
           tp:type="Qualified_Property_Value_Map">
        <tp:docstring>Immutable properties of the sidecar.</tp:docstring>
      </arg>

      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Request an object with a particular interface providing additional
          connection-specific functionality, together with its immutable
          properties. These will often be implemented by plug-ins to the
          connection managers; for example, support for an XMPP XEP for which
          no generic Telepathy interface exists might be implemented by a
          Gabble plugin exposing a sidecar with a particular interface.</p>

        <p>This method may be called at any point during the lifetime of a
          connection, even before its <tp:type>Connection_Status</tp:type>
          changes to Connected. It MAY take a long time to
          return—perhaps it needs to wait for a connection to be established
          and for all the services supported by the server to be discovered
          before determining whether necessary server-side support is
          available—so callers SHOULD override the default method timeout (25
          seconds) with a much higher value (perhaps even MAX_INT32, meaning
          “no timeout” in recent versions of libdbus).</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          <p>There is an implicit assumption that any connection
            manager plugin will only want to export one “primary” object per
            feature it implements, since there is a one-to-one mapping between
            interface and object. This is reasonable since Sidecars are
            (intended to be) analogous to extra interfaces on the connection,
            providing once-per-connection shared functionality; it also makes
            client code straightforward (look up the interface you care about
            in a dictionary, build a proxy object from the value). More
            “plural” plugins are likely to want to implement new types of
            <tp:dbus-ref
              namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy">Channel</tp:dbus-ref>
            instead.</p>
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>

      <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotImplemented">
        <tp:docstring>
          The requested sidecar is not implemented by this connection manager,
          or a necessary server-side component does not exist. (FIXME: split
          these two errors out? Then again, once we list the guaranteed and
          possible sidecars on a Protocol object, clients can tell the
          difference themselves, because they shouldn't be calling this in the
          first case.)
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:error>

      <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.ServiceBusy">
        <tp:docstring>
          A server-side component needed by the requested sidecar reported it
          is currently too busy, or did not respond for some
          implementation-defined time. The caller may wish to try again later.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:error>

      <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.Cancelled">
        <tp:docstring>
          The connection was disconnected while the sidecar was being set up.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:error>
    </method>

  </interface>
</node>
