<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Connection_Interface_Simple_Presence" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2005-2008 Collabora Limited </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2005, 2006 Nokia Corporation </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2006 INdT </tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
      under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as published by
      the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of the License, or (at
      your option) any later version.</p>

    <p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
      WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
      MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU Lesser
      General Public License for more details.</p>

    <p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public License
      along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation,
      Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>

  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection.Interface.SimplePresence">
    <tp:requires interface="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Connection"/>

    <tp:struct name="Simple_Presence">
      <tp:docstring>
        A struct representing the presence of a contact.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Connection_Presence_Type" name="Type">
        <tp:docstring>
          The presence type, e.g. Connection_Presence_Type_Away.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="s" name="Status">
        <tp:docstring>
          The string identifier of the status, e.g. "brb", as defined in the
          <tp:member-ref>Statuses</tp:member-ref> property.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="s" name="Status_Message">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          <p>The user-defined status message, e.g. "Back soon!".</p>

          <p>Clients SHOULD set the status message for the local
            user to the empty string, unless the user has actually provided
            a specific message (i.e. one that conveys more information than the
            Status).</p>

          <p>User interfaces SHOULD regard an empty status message as unset,
            and MAY replace it with a localized string corresponding to the
            Status or Type.</p>

          <tp:rationale>
            Use case: Daf sets his status in Empathy by choosing the Welsh
            translation of "Available" from a menu.
            It is more informative for his English-speaking colleagues
            to see the English translation of "Available" (as localized
            by their own clients) than to see "Ar Gael" (which they don't
            understand anyway).
          </tp:rationale>
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
    </tp:struct>

    <tp:mapping name="Simple_Contact_Presences">
      <tp:docstring>
        Mapping returned by <tp:member-ref>GetPresences</tp:member-ref>
        and signalled by <tp:member-ref>PresencesChanged</tp:member-ref>,
        indicating the presence of a number of contacts.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Contact_Handle" name="Contact">
        <tp:docstring>
          A contact
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="(uss)" tp:type="Simple_Presence" name="Presence">
        <tp:docstring>
          The contact's presence
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
    </tp:mapping>

    <tp:struct name="Simple_Status_Spec">
      <tp:docstring>
        A struct containing information about a status.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:member type="u" tp:type="Connection_Presence_Type" name="Type">
        <tp:docstring>
          The type of a presence. This SHOULD NOT be used as a way to set
          statuses that the client does not recognise (as explained in
          <tp:member-ref>SetPresence</tp:member-ref>), but MAY be used to check
          that the client's assumptions about a particular status name
          match the connection manager's.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="b" name="May_Set_On_Self">
        <tp:docstring>
          If true, the user can set this status on themselves using
          <tp:member-ref>SetPresence</tp:member-ref>.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="b" name="Can_Have_Message">
        <tp:docstring>
          If true, a non-empty message can be set for this status. Otherwise,
          the empty string is the only acceptable message.

          <tp:rationale>
            On IRC you can be Away with a status message, but if you are
            available you cannot set a status message.
          </tp:rationale>
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
    </tp:struct>

    <tp:mapping name="Simple_Status_Spec_Map">
      <tp:docstring>
        A mapping describing possible statuses.
      </tp:docstring>

      <tp:member type="s" name="Identifier">
        <tp:docstring>
          The string identifier of this status.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
      <tp:member type="(ubb)" tp:type="Simple_Status_Spec" name="Spec">
        <tp:docstring>
          Details of this status.
        </tp:docstring>
      </tp:member>
    </tp:mapping>

    <method name="SetPresence" tp:name-for-bindings="Set_Presence">
      <arg direction="in" name="Status" type="s">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          <p>The string identifier of the desired status. Possible status
            identifiers are defined in the
            <tp:member-ref>Statuses</tp:member-ref> property.</p>

          <p>Clients MUST NOT set a status whose string value they do not
            recognise, even if its presence type in Statuses
            matches what the user requested.</p>

          <tp:rationale>
            <p>Suppose a protocol has statuses that include 'phone' (of type
              BUSY) and 'in-a-meeting' (of type BUSY), but there is no
              generic 'busy' status.</p>

            <p>If the user requests "Busy" status from a menu, a
              client author might be tempted to pick an arbitrary status
              that has type BUSY. However, on this protocol, neither of
              the choices would be appropriate, and incorrect information
              about the user would be conveyed.</p>
          </tp:rationale>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="Status_Message" type="s">
        <tp:docstring>
          The status message associated with the current status.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Request that the presence status and status message are published for
          the connection.  Changes will be indicated by
          <tp:member-ref>PresencesChanged</tp:member-ref>
          signals being emitted.</p>

        <p>This method may be called on a newly-created connection while it
          is still in the DISCONNECTED state, to request that when the
          connection connects, it will do so with the selected status.</p>

        <p>In DISCONNECTED state the
          <tp:member-ref>Statuses</tp:member-ref>
          property will indicate which statuses are allowed to be set
          while DISCONNECTED (none, if the Connection Manager doesn't allow
          this). This value MUST NOT be cached, as the set of allowed
          presences might change upon connecting.</p>
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidArgument">
          <tp:docstring>
            Either the specified status is not supported, the specified
            status cannot be set on the user themselves, or a non-empty
            message was supplied for a status that does not
            accept a message.
          </tp:docstring>
        </tp:error>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <method name="GetPresences" tp:name-for-bindings="Get_Presences">
      <arg direction="in" name="Contacts" type="au" tp:type="Contact_Handle[]">
        <tp:docstring>
          An array of the contacts whose presence should be obtained.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" name="Presence" type="a{u(uss)}"
        tp:type="Simple_Contact_Presences">
        <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
          <p>Presence information in the same format as for the
            <tp:member-ref>PresencesChanged</tp:member-ref> signal.
            The returned mapping MUST include an entry for each contact
            in the method's argument.</p>

          <p>The definition of the connection presence types Unknown
            and Offline means that if a connection manager will return
            Unknown for contacts not on the subscribe list, it MUST delay
            the reply to this method call until it has found out which
            contacts are, in fact, on the subscribe list.</p>
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Get presence previously emitted by PresencesChanged for the given
        contacts. Data is returned in the same structure as the
        PresencesChanged signal; no additional network requests are made.
      </tp:docstring>
      <tp:possible-errors>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.Disconnected"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.InvalidHandle"/>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NetworkError">
          <tp:docstring>
            While discovering the subscribe list in order to distinguish
            between Unknown and Offline statuses, a network error occurred.
          </tp:docstring>
        </tp:error>
        <tp:error name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error.NotAvailable"/>
      </tp:possible-errors>
    </method>

    <property name="Statuses" tp:name-for-bindings="Statuses" access="read"
      type="a{s(ubb)}" tp:type="Simple_Status_Spec_Map">
      <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>A dictionary where the keys are the presence statuses that the user
          can set on themselves for this connection, and the values are the
          corresponding presence types.</p>

        <p>While the connection is in the DISCONNECTED state, it contains
          the set of presence statuses allowed to be set before connecting.
          The connection manager will attempt to set the appropriate status
          when the connection becomes connected, but cannot necessarily
          guarantee it. The available statuses cannot change until the
          connection status changes, so there is no change notification.</p>

        <p>While the connection is in the CONNECTED state, this property
          contains the set of presence statuses which are actually available
          on this protocol. This set is constant for the remaining lifetime
          of the connection, so again, there is no change notification.</p>

        <p>While the connection is in the CONNECTING state, the value of
          this property is undefined and SHOULD NOT be used. It can change
          at any time without notification (in particular, any cached values
          from when the connection was in the DISCONNECTED or CONNECTING
          state MUST NOT be assumed to still be correct when the state has
          become CONNECTED).</p>

        <p>This property MUST include the special statuses "unknown" and
          "error" if and only if the connection manager can emit them
          as a contact's status.</p>

        <tp:rationale>
          For instance, connection managers for local-xmpp (XEP-0174) would
          omit "unknown" since there is no such concept.
        </tp:rationale>
      </tp:docstring>
    </property>

    <signal name="PresencesChanged" tp:name-for-bindings="Presences_Changed">
      <arg name="Presence" type="a{u(uss)}" tp:type="Simple_Contact_Presences">
        <tp:docstring>
          A dictionary of contact handles mapped to the status,
          presence type and status message.
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        This signal should be emitted when your own presence has been changed,
        or the presence of the member of any of the connection's channels has
        been changed.
      </tp:docstring>
    </signal>

    <tp:docstring xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>This interface is for services which have a concept of presence which
        can be published for yourself and monitored on your contacts.</p>

      <p>Presence on an individual (yourself or one of your contacts) is
        modelled as a status and a status message. Valid statuses are defined
        per connection, and a list of those that can be set on youself
        can be obtained from the
        <tp:member-ref>Statuses</tp:member-ref>
        property.</p>

      <p>Each status has an arbitrary string identifier which should have an
        agreed meaning between the connection manager and any client which is
        expected to make use of it. The following well-known values should be
        used where possible to allow clients to identify common choices:</p>

      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>status identifier</th>
          <th>Connection_Presence_Type</th>
          <th>comments</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>available</td>
          <td>Connection_Presence_Type_Available</td>
          <td></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>away</td>
          <td>Connection_Presence_Type_Away</td>
          <td></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>brb</td>
          <td>Connection_Presence_Type_Away</td>
          <td>Be Right Back (a more specific form of Away)</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>busy</td>
          <td>Connection_Presence_Type_Busy</td>
          <td></td>
        </tr>
        <tr><td>dnd</td>
          <td>Connection_Presence_Type_Busy</td>
          <td>Do Not Disturb (a more specific form of Busy)</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>xa</td>
          <td>Connection_Presence_Type_Extended_Away</td>
          <td>Extended Away</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>hidden</td>
          <td>Connection_Presence_Type_Hidden</td>
          <td>Also known as "Invisible" or "Appear Offline"</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>offline</td>
          <td>Connection_Presence_Type_Offline</td>
          <td></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>unknown</td>
          <td>Connection_Presence_Type_Unknown</td>
          <td>special, see below</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>error</td>
          <td>Connection_Presence_Type_Error</td>
          <td>special, see below</td>
        </tr>
      </table>

      <p>As well as these well-known status identifiers, every status also has
        a numerical type value chosen from ConnectionPresenceType which can be
        used by the client to classify even unknown statuses into different
        fundamental types.</p>

      <p>These numerical types exist so that even if a client does not
        understand the string identifier being used, and hence cannot present
        the presence to the user to set on themselves, it may display an
        approximation of the presence if it is set on a contact.</p>

      <p>As well as the normal status identifiers, there are two special ones
        that may be present: 'unknown' with type Unknown and 'error' with type
        Error. 'unknown' indicates that it is impossible to determine the
        presence of a contact at this time, for example because it's not on the
        'subscribe' list and the protocol only allows one to determine the
        presence of contacts you're subscribed to. 'error' indicates that there
        was a failure in determining the status of a contact.</p>

      <p>If the connection has a 'subscribe' contact list, PresencesChanged
        signals should be emitted to indicate changes of contacts on this list,
        and should also be emitted for changes in your own presence. Depending
        on the protocol, the signal may also be emitted for others such as
        people with whom you are communicating, and any user interface should
        be updated accordingly.</p>
    </tp:docstring>
  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
