<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tp:errors xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0" namespace="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Error">
  <tp:error name="Network Error">
    <tp:docstring>
    Raised when there is an error reading from or writing to the network.
    </tp:docstring>
  </tp:error>

  <tp:error name="Not Implemented">
    <tp:docstring>
    Raised when the requested method, channel, etc is not available on this connection.
    </tp:docstring>
  </tp:error>

  <tp:error name="Invalid Argument">
    <tp:docstring>
    Raised when one of the provided arguments is invalid.
    </tp:docstring>
  </tp:error>

  <tp:error name="Not Available">
    <tp:docstring>
    Raised when the requested functionality is temporarily unavailable.
    </tp:docstring>
  </tp:error>

  <tp:error name="Permission Denied">
    <tp:docstring>
    The user is not permitted to perform the requested operation.
    </tp:docstring>
  </tp:error>

  <tp:error name="Disconnected">
    <tp:docstring>
    The connection is not currently connected and cannot be used.
    </tp:docstring>
  </tp:error>

  <tp:error name="Invalid Handle">
    <tp:docstring>
    The contact name specified is unknown on this channel or connection.
    </tp:docstring>
  </tp:error>

  <tp:error name="Channel.Banned">
    <tp:docstring>
    You are banned from the channel.
    </tp:docstring>
  </tp:error>

  <tp:error name="Channel.Full">
    <tp:docstring>
    The channel is full.
    </tp:docstring>
  </tp:error>

  <tp:error name="Channel.Invite Only">
    <tp:docstring>
    The requested channel is invite-only.
    </tp:docstring>
  </tp:error>

  <tp:copyright>Copyright (C) 2005, 2006, 2007 Collabora Limited</tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright>Copyright (C) 2005, 2006, 2007 Nokia Corporation</tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
</tp:errors>
