<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<node name="/Media_Session_Handler" xmlns:tp="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/wiki/DbusSpec#extensions-v0">
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2005, 2006 Collabora Limited </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2005, 2006 Nokia Corporation </tp:copyright>
  <tp:copyright> Copyright (C) 2006 INdT </tp:copyright>
  <tp:license xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
version 2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</p>

<p>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.</p>

<p>You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.</p>
  </tp:license>
  <interface name="org.freedesktop.Telepathy.Media.SessionHandler">
    <method name="Error" tp:name-for-bindings="Error">
      <arg direction="in" name="Error_Code" type="u"
        tp:type="Media_Stream_Error"/>
      <arg direction="in" name="Message" type="s"/>
      <tp:docstring>
        THIS METHOD IS DEPRECATED AND SHOULD NOT BE USED. Instead the Error
        function should be used on the relevant MediaStreamHandler objects.
        Informs the connection manager that an error occured in this session.
        If used, the connection manager must terminate the session and all of
        the streams within it, and may also emit a StreamError signal on the
        channel for each stream within the session.
      </tp:docstring>
    </method>
    <signal name="NewStreamHandler" tp:name-for-bindings="New_Stream_Handler">
      <arg name="Stream_Handler" type="o">
        <tp:docstring>
          An object path to a new MediaStreamHandler
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="ID" type="u">
        <tp:docstring>
          The unique ID of the new stream
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="Media_Type" type="u" tp:type="Media_Stream_Type">
        <tp:docstring>
          Enum for type of media that this stream should handle
          (a value from MediaStreamType)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <arg name="Direction" type="u" tp:type="Media_Stream_Direction">
        <tp:docstring>
          Enum for direction of this stream (a value from
          MediaStreamDirection)
        </tp:docstring>
      </arg>
      <tp:docstring>
        Emitted when a new stream handler has been created for this
        session.
      </tp:docstring>
    </signal>
    <method name="Ready" tp:name-for-bindings="Ready">
      <tp:docstring>
        Inform the connection manager that a client is ready to handle
        this session handler (i.e. that it has connected to the
        NewStreamHandler signal and done any other necessary setup).
      </tp:docstring>
    </method>
    <tp:docstring>
      An media session handler is an object that handles a number of synchronised
    media streams.
    </tp:docstring>
  </interface>
</node>
<!-- vim:set sw=2 sts=2 et ft=xml: -->
